<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cupid's courtship, or, The celebration of a marriage between the god of love and Psiche</title>
            <author>Marmion, Shackerley, 1603-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09955437</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09955437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52005)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1363:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cupid's courtship, or, The celebration of a marriage between the god of love and Psiche</title>
                  <author>Marmion, Shackerley, 1603-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.O. for Thomas Dring,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A moral poem on the marriage of Cupid and Psiche.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed October 29, 1666. Roger L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Shackerley Marmion.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cupid</hi>'s <hi>Courtſhip:</hi> OR The Celebration OF A MARRIAGE BETWEEN The God of Love AND PSICHE.</p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>October</hi> 29. 1666.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. O.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> at the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lion</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Chancery-lane;</hi> 1666</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:44380:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44380:2"/>
            <head>To his loving friend, Mr. <hi>S. M.</hi> the Auhour.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRiend, I have read thy <hi>Poem,</hi> full of wit,</l>
               <l>A Maſter-piece, Ile ſet my ſeal to it:</l>
               <l>Let Judges read, and ignorance be gone:</l>
               <l>'Tis not for vulgar thumbs to ſweat upon</l>
               <l>This learned work: thy Muſe flies in her place:</l>
               <l>And Eagle-like, looks <hi>Phoebus</hi> in the face.</l>
               <l>Let thoſe voluminous Authours that affect</l>
               <l>Fame, rather great than good, thy worth reject.</l>
               <l>Jewels are ſmall: how 'nlike art thou to thoſe,</l>
               <l>That tire out Rhime, and Verſe, till they trot Proſe?</l>
               <l>And ride the Muſes <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> poor jade,</l>
               <l>Till he be foundred; and make that their trade:</l>
               <l>And to fill up the ſufferings of the beaſt,</l>
               <l>Foot for themſelves three hundred miles at leaſt.</l>
               <l>Theſe have no mercy on the Paper rheams,</l>
               <l>But produce plays, as School-boys do write theams.</l>
               <l>Thou keepſt thy Muſe in breath, and if men wage</l>
               <l>Gold on her head, will better run the ſtage:</l>
               <l>And 'tis more praiſe, than hadſt thou labour'd in 't,</l>
               <l>To brand the world with twenty ſuch in print.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:44380:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of my worthy friend, Mr.</hi> S. M. <hi>upon his Poem, of</hi> Cupid <hi>and</hi> Pſiche.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOve</hi> and the <hi>Soul</hi> are two things both <hi>Divine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now thy task dear friend, which once was mine.</l>
               <l>What I writ was Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matical thy <hi>Muſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was in an Epick ſtrain, which they ſtill uſe,</l>
               <l>Who write Heroick Poems. Thine is ſuch,</l>
               <l>Which when I read, I could not praiſe too much.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Argument</hi> is high, and not within</l>
               <l>Their ſhallow reach to catch, who hold no ſin</l>
               <l>To tax, what they conceive not; the beſt minds</l>
               <l>Judge trees by fruit, not by their leaves and rinds.</l>
               <l>And ſuch can find (full knowledge having gain'd)</l>
               <l>In leaden Fables, golden truths contain'd.</l>
               <l>Thy ſubjects of that nature a ſublime</l>
               <l>And weighty rapture, which being cloath'd in rime,</l>
               <l>Carries ſuch ſweetneſs with't, as hadſt thou ſung</l>
               <l>Unto <hi>Apollos</hi> Harpe, being newly ſtrung.</l>
               <l>Theſe, had they iſſued from anothers Pen,</l>
               <l>A ſtranger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and unknown to me, I then</l>
               <l>Could not ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e been ſo pleas'd: But from a friend,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> envy, I muſt now command.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I am his fair courſe thou haſt run,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſet my ſelf ſo far ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>one.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> who m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> love prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs,</l>
               <l>More's not requir'd, and mine could ſhow no leſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:44380:3"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>THere were inhabiting in a certain City a King and Queen, who had three Daughters; the elder two of a moderate and mean beauty, but the youngeſt was of ſo curious, ſo pleaſing a feature, and exact ſymmetry of body, that men eſteem'd her generally a <hi>goddeſs,</hi> and the <hi>Venus</hi> of the earth. Her Siſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happily married to their deſires and dignities, ſhe onely, out of a ſuper-excellency of perfection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came rather the ſubject of adoration then <hi>Love. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> conceiving an offence, and envious of her good parts, incites <hi>Cupid</hi> to a revenge, and ſevere vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Mother's honour. <hi>Cupid,</hi> like a fine Archer, coming to execute his Mother's deſign, falls in love with the <hi>Maid,</hi> and wounds himſelf. <hi>Apollo,</hi> by <hi>Cupid</hi>'s ſubornation, adjudges her in marriage to a <hi>Serpent.</hi> Upon which, like <hi>Andromeda,</hi> ſhe is left chain'd to a Rock, her marriage being celebrated ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with funeral obſequies then hymenaeal ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. In this miſerable afright ſhe is born far away by the Weſt-wind to a goodly fair Houſe, whoſe wealth and ſtatelineſs no praiſe can determine. Her Husband in the deadneſs and ſolitude of night did oft-times enjoy her, and as he entred in obſcurity, ſo he departed in ſilence, without once making himſelf known unto her. Thus ſhe continued for a long ſeaſon, being onely waited upon by the miniſtery of the Winds and Voices. Her Siſters came every day to ſeek and bewail her; and though her Husband did
<pb facs="tcp:44380:4"/>with many threats prohibit her the ſight of them, yet natural affection prevailed above conjugal duty, for ſhe never ceaſed with tears to ſolicit him, till he had permitted their acceſs. They no ſooner arrived, but inſtantly corrupt her, and with wicked counſel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prave her underſtanding, infuſing a belief that ſhe had married and did nightly embrace a true Serpent; nor are they yet contented to turn the heaven of her ſecurity into the hell of ſuſpicion, but with many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities proceed, exhorting her to kill him, which ſhe alſo aſſents unto: Thus credulity proves the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of deceit, and curioſity the ſtep-mother of ſafety. Having thus prepat'd for his deſtruction, the Scene is alter'd, and ſhe acts the Tragedy of her own happy fortunes; for coming with an intent to miſchief him, ſo ſoon as the light had diſcovered what he was, ſhe falls into an extremity of love and paſſion, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together raviſh'd with his beauty and habiliments; and while ſhe kiſſes him with as little modeſty as care, the burning Lamp drops upon his ſhoulder, whereupon her Husband furiouſly awakes, and having with many expoſtulations abandon'd her falſhood, ſcorns and forſakes her. The <hi>Maid</hi> after a tedious pilgrimage to regain his love and ſociety, <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> having both repulſed her, freely at the laſt offers up her ſelf to <hi>Venus,</hi> where through her injunctions and imperious commands ſhe is courſely intreated, and ſet to many hard and grievous tasks; as firſt, the ſeperation of ſeveral grains, with the ferching of the <hi>Stygian</hi> water, and the Golden fleece, and the Box
<pb facs="tcp:44380:4"/>of Beauty from <hi>Proſerpine:</hi> all which by divine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance being performed, ſhe is reconcil'd, and in the preſence of all the gods married to her Husband: The Wedding is ſolemnized in Heaven.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation">
            <head>The MYTHOLOGY: OR Explanation of the Argument.</head>
            <p>BY the City is meant the world: by the King and Queen, God and Nature: by the two elder Siſters, the Fleſh and the Will: by the laſt, the Soul, which is the moſt beautiful, and the youngest, ſince ſhe is infuſed after the body is faſhioned: <hi>Venus,</hi> by which is underſtood Luſt, is feigned to envy her, and ſtir up <hi>Cupid,</hi> which is Deſire, to destroy her; but becauſe Deſire has equal relation both to Good and Evil, he is here brought in to love the Soul, and to be joyn'd with her, whom alſo he perſuades not to ſee his face, that is, not to learn his delights and vanities: for <hi>Adam,</hi> though he were naked, yet he ſaw it not, till he had eaten of the Tree of concupiſcence.
<pb facs="tcp:44380:5"/>And whereas ſhe is ſaid to burn him with the diſpumation of the Lamp, by that is underſtood that ſhe vomits out the flames of deſire which was hid in her breaſt; for deſire, the more it is kindled, the more it burns, and makes, as it were, a bliſter in the mind. Thus, like <hi>Eve,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made naked through deſire, ſhe is caſt out of all happineſs, exil'd from her houſe, and toſt with many dangers: By <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> both repulſing of her is meant, that neither wealth nor honour can ſuccour a diſtreſſed ſoul: In the ſeparation of ſeveral grains, is underſtood the act of the Soul, which is recollection, and the ſubſtance of that act, her fore-paſt ſins: By her going to Hell, and thoſe ſeveral occurrences, are meant the many degrees of deſpair: By the <hi>Stygian</hi> water, the tears of repentance: and by the Golden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleece, her forgivneſs. All which, as in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is ſpecified, being by Divine Providence accompliſh'd, ſhe is married to her Spouſe in Heaven.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44380:5"/>
            <head>A MORAL POEM On the Marriage of <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PID</hi> and <hi>PSICHE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>THE FIRST SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth ſays of old, and we muſt owe that truth</l>
                  <l>Unto tradition, when the world in youth,</l>
                  <l>Which was the Golden <hi>Age,</hi> brought forth the <hi>Pen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love</hi> and the <hi>Muſes,</hi> which ſince gave to men</l>
                  <l>Inheritance of Fame, for theſe began</l>
                  <l>At once, and were all coetanean.</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44380:6"/>
                  <l>A happy ſeaſon, when the Air was clear;</l>
                  <l>No ſickneſs nor infection did appear,</l>
                  <l>No ſullen change of ſeaſons did moleſt</l>
                  <l>The fruitful foil, but the whole year was bleſt</l>
                  <l>With a perpetual <hi>Spring,</hi> no <hi>Winter</hi> ſtorm</l>
                  <l>Did criſp the <hi>Hills,</hi> nor mildew blaſt the <hi>Corn:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet happier far, in that it forth did bring</l>
                  <l>The ſubject of this Verſe, whereof I ſing.</l>
                  <l>Under the <hi>Zenith</hi> of Heavens milk-white way,</l>
                  <l>Is a fair Country call'd <hi>Luſinia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis Nature's chiefeſt Wardrobe, where doth lie</l>
                  <l>Her Ornaments of chief variety,</l>
                  <l>Where firſt her glorious Mantle ſhe puts on,</l>
                  <l>When through the world ſhe rides proceſſion:</l>
                  <l>Here dwelt a King and Queen of mighty power,</l>
                  <l>Judg'd for their vertues worthy ſuch a Dower.</l>
                  <l>They had betwixt themſelves three Daughters born,</l>
                  <l>Conſpicuous for their comelineſs and form;</l>
                  <l>The elder two did neither much excel,</l>
                  <l>But then the younger had no parallel;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe lovely cheeks with heavenly luſtre ſhone,</l>
                  <l>And eyes were far too bright to look upon:</l>
                  <l>Nay, it is credible, though fancies wing</l>
                  <l>Should mount above the <hi>Orbs,</hi> and thence down bring</l>
                  <l>Th' Elixar of all beauty, and diſpenſe</l>
                  <l>Unto one creature, the whole influence,</l>
                  <l>And harmony of the Spheres, it might not dare</l>
                  <l>With her for face and feature to compare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Zeuxis</hi> the Painter, who to draw one piece,</l>
                  <l>Survey'd the choifeſt Virgins of all <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44380:6"/>
                  <l>Had reſted here, his Art, without this ſtir,</l>
                  <l>Might have been bounded and confin'd in her.</l>
                  <l>Look how the ſpiced fields in <hi>Autumn</hi> ſmell,</l>
                  <l>And rich Perfumes that in <hi>Arabia</hi> dwell;</l>
                  <l>Such was her fragrant ſweetneſs. The Sun's Bird,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> fled far of, and was afeard</l>
                  <l>To be ſeen near, leſt ſhe his pride ſhould quell,</l>
                  <l>Or make him ſeem a common ſpectacle.</l>
                  <l>Nor did the painted <hi>Peacock</hi> once preſume</l>
                  <l>Within her preſence to diſplay his Plume.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Roſe</hi> nor <hi>Lilly</hi> durſt their Silks unfold,</l>
                  <l>But ſhut their leaves up like the <hi>Marigold.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They all had been ill-favour'd, ſhe alone</l>
                  <l>Was judg'd the Miſtreſs of perfection.</l>
                  <l>Her fame ſpread far abroad, and thither brought</l>
                  <l>Thouſands, that gazing worſhip'd her, and thought</l>
                  <l>The goddeſs, whom the green-fac'd Sea had bred,</l>
                  <l>And dew of foaming waves had nouriſhed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> her self, regardleſs of her honour,</l>
                  <l>Did live with Mortals. Whoſoe'r look'd on her,</l>
                  <l>Even moſt prophane, did think ſhe was divine,</l>
                  <l>And grudg'd not to do worſhip to her ſhrine.</l>
                  <l>For this cauſe <hi>Venus</hi> Temples were defac'd,</l>
                  <l>Her Sacrifice and Ceremonies rac'd;</l>
                  <l>Her widow'd Altars in cold aſhes mourn'd,</l>
                  <l>Her Images uncrown'd, her Groves deform'd:</l>
                  <l>Her Rites were all polluted with contempt,</l>
                  <l>For none to <hi>Paphos</hi> nor <hi>Cytheros</hi> went.</l>
                  <l>This Maid was ſole ador'd. <hi>Venus</hi> diſpleas'd,</l>
                  <l>Might in this Virgin onely be appeas'd.</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44380:7"/>
                  <l>The people in the ſtreet to her would bow,</l>
                  <l>And as ſhe paſs'd along would Garlands ſtrow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> at this conceiv'd a jealous ire,</l>
                  <l>(For heavenly minds burn with an earthly fire)</l>
                  <l>And ſpake with indignation, What, ſhall I,</l>
                  <l>Mother of Elements, and loftieſt skie,</l>
                  <l>Beginner of the world, Parent of Nature,</l>
                  <l>Pertake mine honour with an earthly creature?</l>
                  <l>Shall ſilly Girls, deſtin'd to death and fate,</l>
                  <l>My high-born name and ſtile contaminate?</l>
                  <l>In vain did then the <hi>Phrygian</hi> Shepherds give</l>
                  <l>The Ball to me, when three of us did ſtrive</l>
                  <l>Who ſhould excel in beauty, and all ſtood</l>
                  <l>Naked before the Boy, to tempt his bloud,</l>
                  <l>When they with Royal gifts ſought to beguile</l>
                  <l>His judgment, I alur'd him with a ſmile.</l>
                  <l>But this uſurper of my dignities,</l>
                  <l>Shall have but little cauſe to boaſt the prize.</l>
                  <l>With that ſhe call'd her raſh and winged Child,</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with Bow, Torch and Quiver; that is wild</l>
                  <l>With miſchief, he that with his evil ways</l>
                  <l>Corrupts all publick diſcipline, and ſtrays</l>
                  <l>Through Chambers in the night, &amp; with falſe beam</l>
                  <l>Or with his ſtinging Arrows, or with dreams,</l>
                  <l>Tempts unto luſt, and does no good at all:</l>
                  <l>This Child, I ſay, did <hi>Venus</hi> to her call,</l>
                  <l>And ſtirs him up with words malitious,</l>
                  <l>That was by nature too licentious:</l>
                  <l>For bringing him where <hi>Pſyche</hi> dwelt, for ſo</l>
                  <l>This Maid was call'd, ſhe there unfolds her woe,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:44380:7"/>
                  <l>And emulous tale. <hi>Cupid,</hi> quoth ſhe, my ſtay,</l>
                  <l>My onely ſtrength and power, whoſe boundleſs ſway,</l>
                  <l>Contemns the thunder of my father <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I here intreat thee by thy Mother's love.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wounding ſweets, and ſweet wounds of thy Quiver,</l>
                  <l>And hony burnings of thy Torch, deliver</l>
                  <l>My ſoul from grief, revenge me on this Maid,</l>
                  <l>And all her boaſted beauty ſee decaid,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſtrike her in love with one ſo poor,</l>
                  <l>So miſerably loſt, ſtript of all ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of means or vertue; ſo deform'd of limb,</l>
                  <l>That none in all the world may equal him.</l>
                  <l>To move her ſon, no flattering words ſhe ſpar'd,</l>
                  <l>But breath'd on him with kiſſes, long and hard,</l>
                  <l>This done, ſhe haſtes to the next ebbing ſhore,</l>
                  <l>And with her roſie feet inſulting o'r</l>
                  <l>The ſubmiſs waves, a <hi>Dolphin</hi> ſhe beſtrides,</l>
                  <l>And on the utmoſt Billows proudly rides.</l>
                  <l>A troup of <hi>Tritons</hi> were ſtreight ſounding heard,</l>
                  <l>And rough <hi>Portumnus</hi> with his moſſy beard,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Salacia</hi> heavy with her fiſhy train,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Nereus</hi> daughters came to entertain</l>
                  <l>The Sea-born goddeſs; ſome plaid on a ſhell,</l>
                  <l>Some with their garments labour'd to expel</l>
                  <l>The ſcorching heat, and Sun-ſhine from her face,</l>
                  <l>And other ſome did hold a Looking-glaſs:</l>
                  <l>All theſe in triumph by the <hi>Dolphin</hi> ſwam,</l>
                  <l>And follow'd <hi>Venus</hi> to the Ocean.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> the while, in this great height of bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Yet reaps no fruit of all her happineſs,</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44380:8"/>
                  <l>For neither King, nor Prince, nor Potentate,</l>
                  <l>Nor any durſt attempt her for a Mate,</l>
                  <l>But as a poliſh'd picture her admire,</l>
                  <l>And in that admiration ceaſe deſire:</l>
                  <l>Her Sifters both, whoſe moderate beauty none</l>
                  <l>Did much deſpiſe, nor much contemplate on,</l>
                  <l>Were to their wiſhes happily contracted,</l>
                  <l>And by two Kings eſpous'd. <hi>Pſiche</hi> diſtracted</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhe had no Lover, penſive ſate</l>
                  <l>In mind and body, and began to hate,</l>
                  <l>And curſe that beauty, and eſteem at nought,</l>
                  <l>Which, but was excellent, had no other fault.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> now in a cauſeleſs rage was gone</l>
                  <l>To whet his Arrows on a bloudy ſtone,</l>
                  <l>As if he were t'encounter with ſome main</l>
                  <l>Monſter, like <hi>Python,</hi> by <hi>Apollo</hi> ſlain,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Jove,</hi> or <hi>Titan</hi> lame, or once agen</l>
                  <l>Draw the pale Moon down to the <hi>Latmian</hi> Den,</l>
                  <l>Or with Love's fire great <hi>Pluto</hi> to annoy,</l>
                  <l>For theſe were works of <hi>labour,</hi> and the Boy</l>
                  <l>Was ignorant, how matters would ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>Or what the fate of Beauty had decreed.</l>
                  <l>Therefore he fil'd his Arrows ſharp and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>To pierce what ever they ſhould meet withall;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And vow'd,</hi> if cauſe were, he his <hi>ſhaft,</hi> would ſhiver</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Pſiche</hi>'s breaſt, and empty all his Quiver.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Themis</hi> a goddeſs, whom great <hi>Jove</hi> had ſent</l>
                  <l>Into the world; for good or puniſhment,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As Justice</hi> ſhould require, when ſhe did hear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> ſo proudly boaſt, again did ſwear,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44380:8"/>
                  <l>That <hi>ſhe</hi> his haughty malice would abate,</l>
                  <l>And turn the edge both of his <hi>ſhafts</hi> and <hi>hate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And having thus diſarm'd him, ten to one,</l>
                  <l>Would change his <hi>fury</hi> to <hi>affection.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A clap of <hi>Thunder</hi> all about them ſhook,</l>
                  <l>To ratifie what <hi>Themis</hi> undertook.</l>
                  <l>Then both together went, and entring, found</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Pſiche,</hi> with her looks fix'd on the ground.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Modeſty,</hi> with equal grace,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Simplicity</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> ſmil'd in her face.</l>
                  <l>But riſing up, their ſhot from either eye</l>
                  <l>Such beams, as did <hi>Love</hi>'s ſenſes ſtupefie.</l>
                  <l>And as in this diſtraction <hi>he</hi> did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He</hi> let his <hi>Arrows</hi> fall out of his hand:</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Themis,</hi> laughing, took, and thence convey'd,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Cupid</hi> minding nothing but the <hi>Maid.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then did <hi>he</hi> cry amaz'd, What fence is here?</l>
                  <l>Beauty and Vertue have no other ſphere;</l>
                  <l>Her brow's a Caſtle, and each lip a Fort,</l>
                  <l>Where thouſand armed Deities reſort</l>
                  <l>To guard the golden fruit from all ſurprize,</l>
                  <l>Chaſtly, and ſafe, as the <hi>Heſperides.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pardon me, <hi>Venus,</hi> if I thee abridge</l>
                  <l>Of this unjuſt revenge; 'twere ſacrilege,</l>
                  <l>Beyond <hi>Prometheus</hi> theft, to quench ſuch fire,</l>
                  <l>Or ſteal it from <hi>her</hi> eyes, but to inſpire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi>'s own breaſt, in all <hi>Love</hi>'s ſpoiles, I yet</l>
                  <l>Never beheld ſo rich a Cabinet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove,</hi> here for ever, here my heart confine,</l>
                  <l>And let me all my Empery reſign.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44380:9"/>
                  <l>Then looking down, he found himſelf beref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of his looſe Arms, and ſmil'd at <hi>Themis</hi> theft,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he knew ſhe might as ſoon abide</l>
                  <l>Fire in her boſome, as <hi>Love</hi>'s Arrows hide,</l>
                  <l>But that they muſt again with ſhame be ſent,</l>
                  <l>And claim for the poſſeſſion a dear rent:</l>
                  <l>Yet one dropt out by chance, and 'twas the beſt</l>
                  <l>Of all the bundle, and the curiouſeſt;</l>
                  <l>The plumes were colour'd azure, white and red,</l>
                  <l>The ſhaft painted alike down to the head,</l>
                  <l>Which was of burniſh'd gold: this <hi>Cupid</hi> took,</l>
                  <l>And in revenge, through his own boſome ſtrook:</l>
                  <l>Then, ſighing, call'd, You <hi>Lovers</hi> all (in chief)</l>
                  <l>Whom I have wrong'd, come triumph at my grief;</l>
                  <l>See, and be ſatisfi'd for all my ſin,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not one place that I am pained in,</l>
                  <l>My Arrow's venom is diſperſed round,</l>
                  <l>And beauty's ſign is potent in each wound.</l>
                  <l>Thus he with pity did himſelf deplore,</l>
                  <l>For never pity enter'd him before.</l>
                  <l>Ill as he was, he took his flight, and came</l>
                  <l>Unto the Palace of the Sun, whoſe flame</l>
                  <l>Was far inferiour to what <hi>Cupid</hi> felt;</l>
                  <l>And ſaid, Dear <hi>Phoebus,</hi> if I ſtill have dealt</l>
                  <l>Like a true friend, and ſtood thee in ſome ſtead,</l>
                  <l>When thou for love didſt like a ſhepheard ſeed</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Admetus</hi> Cattle, now thine help impart;</l>
                  <l>'Tis not for Phyſick, though I'm ſick at heart,</l>
                  <l>That I implore, but through thy skill divine</l>
                  <l>The faireſt <hi>Pſiche</hi> for my wife aſſign.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44380:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phoebus</hi> aſſents, and did not long delay</l>
                  <l>To make it good by a prophetick way:</l>
                  <l>Her Father fearing for the injury</l>
                  <l>Offer'd to <hi>Venus</hi> ſacred Deity,</l>
                  <l>Conſults the <hi>Delphick</hi> Oracle, who thus</l>
                  <l>Expounds his mind in terms ambiguous.</l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>The Oracle.</head>
                     <l>YOur Daughter bring to a steep Mountain ſpire,</l>
                     <l>Inveſted with a funeral attire;</l>
                     <l>Expect no good, but bind her to a stake,</l>
                     <l>No mortal Wight her for a wife ſhall take:</l>
                     <l>But a huge venom'd Serpent, that does flie</l>
                     <l>With ſpeckled wings, above the starry skie:</l>
                     <l>And down again does the whole Earth moleſt</l>
                     <l>With fire, and ſword, and all kind of unreſt,</l>
                     <l>So great in malice, and ſo ſtrong in might,</l>
                     <l>That Heaven and Hell do tremble at his flight.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <l>The King afrighted what this ſpeech ſhould ween,</l>
                  <l>Goes flow and ſadly home unto his Queen:</l>
                  <l>Both ponder in their mind the ſtrange prediction,</l>
                  <l>Whether it were a Riddle or a Fiction,</l>
                  <l>What gloſs it might endure, and what pretence,</l>
                  <l>Whether a verbal or a miſtick ſenſe.</l>
                  <l>Which caſt about in vain, they both bewail</l>
                  <l>Their Daughters chance, but grief cannot ptevail,</l>
                  <l>But that ſhe muſt ſulfil the <hi>Delphick</hi> doom,</l>
                  <l>Or worſer plagues are threatned in the room.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:44380:10"/>
                  <l>And now the pitchy Torches lighted are,</l>
                  <l>And for her fatal Marriage they prepare;</l>
                  <l>Songs are to houlings turn'd, bright fire to fume,</l>
                  <l>And pleaſant Muſick to the <hi>Lydian</hi> tune:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Hymen's Saffron</hi> weed that ſhould adorn</l>
                  <l>Young bluſhing Brides, <hi>Pſiche</hi> is forc'd to mourn,</l>
                  <l>And for her mourning a black Mantle wears,</l>
                  <l>With which ſhe gently wipes away her tears.</l>
                  <l>Thus all the City wait her in ſad wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Not to her wedding, but her obſequies;</l>
                  <l>But whilſt her parents vain excuſes make,</l>
                  <l>And vain delays, thus <hi>Pſiche</hi> them beſpake:</l>
                  <l>Why do you thus with deep-fetch'd ſighs perplex</l>
                  <l>Your moſt unhappy age? why do you vex</l>
                  <l>Your ſpirit which is mine, and thus diſgrace</l>
                  <l>With fruitleſs tears your venerable face?</l>
                  <l>Why do you tear your hair, and beat your breaſt?</l>
                  <l>Are theſe the hopeful iſſues, and the bleſt</l>
                  <l>Rewards for beauty? then ought you lament,</l>
                  <l>When all the City with a joyn'd conſent</l>
                  <l>Did ſtile me the new <hi>Venus,</hi> and aſcrib'd</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Honours which to Mortals are deni'd.</l>
                  <l>'Twas your ambition firſt pluck'd on my ſhame,</l>
                  <l>I ſee and feel my ruine in her name:</l>
                  <l>'Tis now too late, we ſuffer under thoſe</l>
                  <l>Deep wounds of envy which the gods impoſe;</l>
                  <l>Where is the Rock? why do you linger ſo?</l>
                  <l>Lead hence, me-thinks I long to undergo</l>
                  <l>This happy marriage, and I long to ſee</l>
                  <l>My noble Husband, whatſoe'r he be:</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44380:10"/>
                  <l>Into his arms O let me ſoon be hurl'd</l>
                  <l>That's born for the deſtruction of the world.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, each ſtander by with with hang'd down head</l>
                  <l>And mournful pomp the Virgin followed,</l>
                  <l>And to the place prefix'd her arms they tie,</l>
                  <l>Then houling forth a doleful Elegy,</l>
                  <l>Depart from her in tears, wiſhing from far</l>
                  <l>Some winged <hi>Perſeus</hi> might deliver her.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> afrighted thus, and they all gone,</l>
                  <l>A gentle gale of wind came poſting on,</l>
                  <l>Who with his whiſpers having charm'd her fears,</l>
                  <l>The Maid aſleep on his ſoft boſome bears.</l>
                  <l>This wind is called <hi>Zephirus,</hi> whoſe mild</l>
                  <l>And fruitful birth gets the young Spring with child,</l>
                  <l>Filling her womb with ſuch delicious heat,</l>
                  <l>As breeds the blooming Roſe and Violet:</l>
                  <l>Him <hi>Cupid</hi> for his delicacy choſe,</l>
                  <l>And did this amorous task on him impoſe,</l>
                  <l>To fetch his Miſtreſs; but leſt he ſhould burn</l>
                  <l>With Beauty's fire, he bad him ſoon return:</l>
                  <l>But all in vain, for promiſes are frail,</l>
                  <l>And vertue flies when love once blows the ſail;</l>
                  <l>For as ſhe ſlept, he lingred on his way,</l>
                  <l>And oft embrac'd and kiſs'd her as his prey,</l>
                  <l>And gaz'd to ſee how far ſhe did ſurpaſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Erietheus</hi> daughter, wife to <hi>Boreas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Orythia;</hi> and as ſhe began</l>
                  <l>To wax hot through his motion, he would fan</l>
                  <l>And cool her with his wings, which did diſperſe</l>
                  <l>A perfum'd ſent through all the Univerſe:</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44380:11"/>
                  <l>For fore that time no fragrant ſmell did live</l>
                  <l>In any thing, till <hi>Pſiche</hi> did it give:</l>
                  <l>Herbs, Gums and Spices had perhaps a name,</l>
                  <l>But their firſt Odours from her breathing came:</l>
                  <l>And in this manner <hi>Zephirus</hi> flew on</l>
                  <l>With want on gyres through every Region</l>
                  <l>Of the vaſt Air, then brought her to a vale,</l>
                  <l>Where thouſand ſeveral flowers her ſweets exhale:</l>
                  <l>The whilſt her parents robb'd of her dear ſight,</l>
                  <l>Devote themſelves to everlaſting night.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>The Second Section.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THus <hi>Pſiche</hi> on a graſſie bed did lie,</l>
                  <l>Adorn'd with <hi>Flora</hi>'s richeſt tapeſtry,</l>
                  <l>Where all her ſenſes with ſoft ſlumber bound,</l>
                  <l>At laſt awak'd, and riſing from a ſwound</l>
                  <l>She ſpies a wood, with fair trees beautifi'd,</l>
                  <l>And a pure chryſtal fountain by the ſide;</l>
                  <l>A Kingly palace ſtood not far apart,</l>
                  <l>Built not with humane hands, but divine art;</l>
                  <l>For by the ſtructure men might gheſs it be</l>
                  <l>The habitation of ſome Deity:</l>
                  <l>The roof within was curiouſly o're-ſpread</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Ivory</hi> and Gold enamelled;</l>
                  <l>The Gold was burniſh'd gliſtering like a flame,</l>
                  <l>And golden pillars did ſupport the ſame;</l>
                  <l>The walls were all with Silver wainſcor lin'd,</l>
                  <l>With ſeveral beaſts and pictures there enſhrin'd;</l>
                  <l>The floor and pavement with like glory ſhone,</l>
                  <l>Cut in rare figures made of precious ſtone,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:44380:11"/>
                  <l>That though the Sun ſhould hide his light away,</l>
                  <l>You might behold the houſe through its own day.</l>
                  <l>Sure 'twas ſome wondrous power by <hi>arts</hi> extent</l>
                  <l>That fancied forth ſo great an argument:</l>
                  <l>And no leſs happy they that did command,</l>
                  <l>And with their feet trod on ſo rich a land.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> amax'd, fix'd her delighted eye</l>
                  <l>On the magnificenſe and treaſury,</l>
                  <l>And wonder'd moſt that ſuch a maſs of wealth</l>
                  <l>Was by no door nor guar'd preſerv'd from ſtealth:</l>
                  <l>For looking when ſome ſervant ſhould appear,</l>
                  <l>She onely heard voices attending there,</l>
                  <l>That ſaid, Fair Miſtreſs, why are you afraid?</l>
                  <l>All theſe are yours, and we to do you aid.</l>
                  <l>Come up into the rooms, where ſhall be ſhown</l>
                  <l>Chambers all ready furniſh'd, all your own:</l>
                  <l>From thence deſcend and take the ſpiced air,</l>
                  <l>Or from your bath unto your bed repair,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt each of us, that <hi>Eccho</hi> repreſents,</l>
                  <l>Devoid of all corporeal inftruments,</l>
                  <l>Shall wait your Miniſter: no Princely fare</l>
                  <l>Shall wanting be, no diligence, no care,</l>
                  <l>To do you ſervice. <hi>Pſiche</hi> had the ſenſe</l>
                  <l>To taſte, and thank the god's beneficenſe:</l>
                  <l>When ſtraight a mighty golden diſh was brought,</l>
                  <l>Repleat with all the dainties can be thought;</l>
                  <l>And next a bowle was on the table ſet,</l>
                  <l>Fraught with the richeſt Nectar that ere yet</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>He be</hi> fill'd to <hi>Juno,</hi> Heaven's Queen,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Ganimede</hi> to <hi>Jove;</hi> yet none was ſeen,</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:44380:12"/>
                  <l>Nor creature found to pledge, or to begin,</l>
                  <l>But ſome impulſive ſpirit brought it in.</l>
                  <l>The Banquet ended, there was heard on high</l>
                  <l>A Confort of celeſtial harmony,</l>
                  <l>And Muſick mix'd with ſounds articulate,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſelf might ſtrive to emulate.</l>
                  <l>All pleaſures finiſh'd, <hi>Pſiche</hi> went to reſt,</l>
                  <l>But could find none, becauſe her troubled breaſt</l>
                  <l>Labour'd with ſtrange events, and now the noon</l>
                  <l>Of night began t' approach, and the pale Moon</l>
                  <l>Hid her weak beams, and ſleep had ſeiz'd all eyes,</l>
                  <l>But Lover's, vex'd with fears and jealouſies.</l>
                  <l>VVhat female heart or conſcience ſo ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Through the diſcharge of ſin? but yet among</l>
                  <l>So many fancies of her active brain,</l>
                  <l>She muſt a hundred terrours entertain;</l>
                  <l>And more and greater her amazements were,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhe knew not what ſhe was to fear.</l>
                  <l>In came her dreadful husband ſo conceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Till his ſweet voice told her, ſhe was deceiv'd:</l>
                  <l>For drawing near, he ſate upon the bed,</l>
                  <l>Then laid his gentle hand upon her head,</l>
                  <l>And next embrac'd, and kiſs'd, and did imbrew</l>
                  <l>Her balmy lips with a delicious dew:</l>
                  <l>So, ſo, ſays he, let each give up his treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Quite bankrupt through a rich exchange of pleaſure</l>
                  <l>So let's ſweet <hi>Love's praeludium</hi> begin,</l>
                  <l>My arms ſhall be thy ſphere to wander in,</l>
                  <l>Circled about with ſpells to charm thy fears,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of <hi>Morpheus</hi> to provoke thy tears;</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44380:12"/>
                  <l>VVith horrid dreams <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall thee entrance</l>
                  <l>VVith thouſand ſhapes of wanton dalliance:</l>
                  <l>Each of thy ſenſes thou ſhalt perfect find,</l>
                  <l>All but thy ſight, for <hi>Love</hi> ought to be blind.</l>
                  <l>And having ſaid ſo, he made haſte to bed,</l>
                  <l>Enjoy'd his Spouſe, and got her Maidenhead:</l>
                  <l>And leſt that ſhe his feature ſhould diſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>He went away before the morning roſe:</l>
                  <l>Her vocal ſervants watching at the door,</l>
                  <l>With their mild whiſpers enter'd in before</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> awak'd, and joy'd the Bride to ſee,</l>
                  <l>And cheer'd her for her ſlain virginity.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things being acted in continued time,</l>
                  <l>And as all humane natures do incline</l>
                  <l>To take delight by cuſtome, <hi>Pſiche</hi> ſo</l>
                  <l>With theſe aëreal comforts eas'd her woe.</l>
                  <l>But yet her Parents with unwearied grief</l>
                  <l>VVax'd old in tears and hated all relief.</l>
                  <l>Her ſiſters too forſook their houſe and home,</l>
                  <l>And came to adde unto their father's moan.</l>
                  <l>That night her Husband <hi>Pſiche</hi> thus beſpake,</l>
                  <l>Alas, Sweet-heart, what comfort can I take,</l>
                  <l>That ſpend the day in ſighes when you are gone,</l>
                  <l>Rob'd of all humane converſation?</l>
                  <l>My undiſtinguiſh'd friends are baniſh'd quite,</l>
                  <l>That almoſt weep their eyes out for my ſight,</l>
                  <l>Not one of all to bear me company:</l>
                  <l>O let me ſee my ſiſters or I die.</l>
                  <l>Her Husband her embrac'd and kiſs'd away</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hurtful tears, and thus began to ſay:</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44380:13"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> my ſweet and deareſt wife, I ſee</l>
                  <l>Fortune begins to threat thy miſery.</l>
                  <l>VVhat envious fate ſuggeſts this baneful boon,</l>
                  <l>To force my grief and thy deſtruction?</l>
                  <l>Thy ſiſters both, through their vain fancies led,</l>
                  <l>And troubled with the thought that thou art dead,</l>
                  <l>VVill ſeek thee forth: but if thou should'ſt regard</l>
                  <l>Their fruitleſs tears, or ſpeak to them a word,</l>
                  <l>Or by their wicked counſel ſeek to pry</l>
                  <l>VVith ſacrilegious curioſity,</l>
                  <l>And view my shape, how quickly wouldſt thou throw</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf down headlong to the depth of woe?</l>
                  <l>Thy wretched ſtate for ever to deplore,</l>
                  <l>Nor muſt thou hope to touch me any more.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> regardleſs what his love or fears</l>
                  <l>Did prompt unto her good, ſtill perſeveres</l>
                  <l>In her rash vote: for all (though to their coſt)</l>
                  <l>Deſire forbidden things, but women moſt.</l>
                  <l>My hony husband, my ſweet love, quoth she,</l>
                  <l>How do I prize thee, whatſoe'r thou be?</l>
                  <l>Above my ſoul, more then my own dear life:</l>
                  <l>Nor would I change to be young <hi>Cupid</hi>'s wife,</l>
                  <l>And rather vow'd a thouſand deaths to die,</l>
                  <l>Then live divorc'd from his ſociety.</l>
                  <l>Her husband overcome through his own fire,</l>
                  <l>VVhich her impreſſive kiſſes did inſpire,</l>
                  <l>Gives way to his new Spouſe, and a ſtrict charge</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Zephirus</hi> that he should ſpread at large</l>
                  <l>His plumy ſails, and bring her ſiſters twain,</l>
                  <l>Both ſafe in preſence of his wife, in pain</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44380:13"/>
                  <l>To be in priſon, and ſtrict durance bound</l>
                  <l>With the earths weighty fetters under ground,</l>
                  <l>And a huge mountain to be laid upon</l>
                  <l>His aery back, which if it once were done,</l>
                  <l>No power could e'r redeem his liberty,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Aeolus</hi> himſelf might ſet him free.</l>
                  <l>Lovers commands are ſtill imperious:</l>
                  <l>Which made the fierce and haughty <hi>Zephyrus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Swell with cloſe indignation, and fret</l>
                  <l>To ſee his ſervice ſlighted ſo, but yet</l>
                  <l>Not daring to proclame his diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Made a ſoft noiſe, and murmur'd as he went.</l>
                  <l>By chance her ſiſters at that inſtant time,</l>
                  <l>VVith long laborious ſteps the hill did clime</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Pſiche</hi> firſt was left, and with their plain</l>
                  <l>Waken the Rocks, ſtill they reſult again,</l>
                  <l>Calling their ſiſter by her proper name,</l>
                  <l>With hideous cries, until the weſt wind came,</l>
                  <l>And as command was, in a winged chair,</l>
                  <l>With harmleſs portage bore them through the air.</l>
                  <l>All three together by this means combin'd,</l>
                  <l>Embrace each other with a mutual mind,</l>
                  <l>Until their ſpirits and the day was ſpent</l>
                  <l>In long and ceremonious complement.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes fair <hi>Pſiche,</hi> proud her friends were by,</l>
                  <l>To witneſs her Majeſtick bravery,</l>
                  <l>Uſhering her ſiſters with affected gate,</l>
                  <l>Would ſhew them all her glory and her ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And round about her golden houſe diſplay</l>
                  <l>The maſſie wealth that unregarded lay.</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:44380:14"/>
                  <l>Sometimes ſhe would demonſtrate to their ears</l>
                  <l>Her eaſie power on thoſe familiars,</l>
                  <l>That like a numerous family did ſtand</l>
                  <l>To execure the charge of her command.</l>
                  <l>Nor was there wanting any thing that might</l>
                  <l>Procure their admiration or delight:</l>
                  <l>That whereas erſt they pitied her diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Now ſwell with envy of her happineſs.</l>
                  <l>There is a goddeſs flies through the earth's globe,</l>
                  <l>Girt with a cloud, and in a ſqualid robe,</l>
                  <l>Daughter to <hi>Pluto</hi> and the ſilent Night,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe direful preſence does the <hi>Sun</hi> afright;</l>
                  <l>Her name is <hi>Ate,</hi> venom is her food,</l>
                  <l>The very <hi>Furies</hi> and <hi>Tartarian</hi> brood</l>
                  <l>Do hate her for her uglineſs, ſhe blacks</l>
                  <l>Her horrid viſage with ſo many <hi>Snakes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And as her treſſes 'bout her neck ſhe hurls,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Serpents</hi> hiſs within her knotty curls.</l>
                  <l>Sorrow and ſhame, death and a thouſand woes,</l>
                  <l>And diſcord waits her whereſoe'r ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>VVho riding on a whirl-wind through the sky,</l>
                  <l>She ſaw fair <hi>Pſiche</hi> in her jollity,</l>
                  <l>And grudg'd to ſee it, for ſhe does profeſs</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf a foe to every good ſucceſs:</l>
                  <l>Then caſt to ruine her, but found no way,</l>
                  <l>Leſs ſhe could make her ſiſters her betray.</l>
                  <l>Then drop'd four <hi>Snakes</hi> out of her hairy neſt,</l>
                  <l>And as they ſlept caſt two on eithers breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Who piercing through their boſoms in a trice,</l>
                  <l>Poiſon'd their ſouls, but made no Orifice:</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44380:14"/>
                  <l>And all this while the powerful bane did lurk</l>
                  <l>Within their hearts, and now began to work:</l>
                  <l>For one of them, too far inquiſitive,</l>
                  <l>With crafty malice did begin to dive</l>
                  <l>Into her counſel, ſtudious for to learn</l>
                  <l>Whom ſo divine poſſeſſion might concern;</l>
                  <l>But all in vain, no lineal reſpect,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Syren</hi> charms might move her to reject</l>
                  <l>His precepts, nothing they could do or ſay</l>
                  <l>Might tempt her his ſweet counſels to betray.</l>
                  <l>Yet leſt too much ſuſpence of what he is</l>
                  <l>Should trouble their looſe thoughts, ſhe told them this,</l>
                  <l>He was a fair young man, whoſe downy chin</l>
                  <l>VVas newly deck'd with natures coverin,</l>
                  <l>And he that us'd with hunting ſtill to rome</l>
                  <l>About the woods, and ſeldome was at home.</l>
                  <l>But fearing their diſcourſe might her entrap,</l>
                  <l>She pours forth gold and jewels in their lap,</l>
                  <l>And turning all their travel to their gain,</l>
                  <l>Commands the winds to bear them back again.</l>
                  <l>This done, her ſiſters after their return,</l>
                  <l>With envies fuel, both begin to burn,</l>
                  <l>Unable to contain their diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>And to their ſwell'd up malice give a vent.</l>
                  <l>Says one unto the other, what's the cauſe</l>
                  <l>That we both priviledg'd by nature's laws,</l>
                  <l>And of the ſelf-ſame parents both begot,</l>
                  <l>Should yet ſuſtain ſuch an indifferent lot?</l>
                  <l>You know that we are like to Hand-maids wed</l>
                  <l>To ſtrangers, and like ſtrangers baniſhed.</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44380:15"/>
                  <l>When ſhe, the off-ſpring of a later birth,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from a womb that like the tired earth</l>
                  <l>Grew old with bearing, nor yet very wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Enjoys that wealth whoſe uſe, whoſe worth, whoſe price</l>
                  <l>She knows not; what rich furniture there ſhone,</l>
                  <l>What gems, what gold, what ſilks we tread upon?</l>
                  <l>And if her husband be ſo brave a man,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe affirms and boaſts, what woman can</l>
                  <l>In the whole world compare with her? at length</l>
                  <l>Perhaps by cuſtoms progreſs, and the ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Of love, he may her like himſelf tranſlate,</l>
                  <l>And make her with the gods participate:</l>
                  <l>She has already for to come and go</l>
                  <l>Voices her hand-maids, and the winds, 'tis ſo;</l>
                  <l>She bore her ſelf with no leſs Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>And breath'd out nothing but divinity:</l>
                  <l>But I, poor wretch, the more to aggravate</l>
                  <l>My cares, and the iniquity of fate,</l>
                  <l>Have got a husband, elder then my ſire,</l>
                  <l>And then a boy far weaker in deſire,</l>
                  <l>Who though he have nor will nor power to uſe</l>
                  <l>VVhat he enjoys, does, miſer-like, refuſe</l>
                  <l>To his own wife this benefit to grant,</l>
                  <l>That others ſhould ſupply his and my want.</l>
                  <l>Her ſiſter anſwers, Do not I embrace</l>
                  <l>A man far worſe, and is't not my own caſe?</l>
                  <l>I have a husband too not worth a point,</l>
                  <l>And one that has the Gout in every joint;</l>
                  <l>His noſe is dropping, and his eyes are gumm'd,</l>
                  <l>His body crooked, and his fingers numm'd:</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44380:15"/>
                  <l>His head, which should of wiſdom be the place,</l>
                  <l>Is grown more bald then any Looking-glaſs;</l>
                  <l>That I am fain the part toundergo,</l>
                  <l>Not of a wife but a phyſician too,</l>
                  <l>Still plying him, howe'r my ſenſe it loaths,</l>
                  <l>With oyls, and balms, and cataplaſms and cloaths:</l>
                  <l>Yet you ſee with what patience I endure</l>
                  <l>This ſervile office, and this fruitleſs cure;</l>
                  <l>The whilſt the minks our ſiſter you beheld,</l>
                  <l>VVith how great pride and arrogance ſhe ſwell'd,</l>
                  <l>And though much wealth lay ſcatter'd all along,</l>
                  <l>Yet out of it how ſmall a portion</l>
                  <l>She gave to us, and how unwillingly,</l>
                  <l>Then blew or hiſt us from her company.</l>
                  <l>Let me not breath, nor me a woman call,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs I ſtraight her ruine, or enthral</l>
                  <l>In everlaſting miſery: and firſt</l>
                  <l>In this one point I'll render her accurſt.</l>
                  <l>We will not any into wonder draw,</l>
                  <l>Nor comfort, by relating what we ſaw;</l>
                  <l>For they cannot be ſaid true joy to own,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe neither wealth nor happineſs is known.</l>
                  <l>It is enough that we have ſeen and grieve</l>
                  <l>That we have ſeen it, let none elſe believe</l>
                  <l>The truth from our report. So let's repair</l>
                  <l>To our own home, and our own homely ſare,</l>
                  <l>And then return to vindicate her pride,</l>
                  <l>With fraud and malice ſtrongly fortifi'd:</l>
                  <l>Which to confirm, ungrateful as they were,</l>
                  <l>For wicked counſel ever is moſt dear</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44380:16"/>
                  <l>To wicked people) home again they drew.</l>
                  <l>And their feign'd grief moſt impiouſly renue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>The third Section.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BY this fair <hi>Pſiche</hi>'s womb began to breed,</l>
                  <l>And was made pregnant by immortal ſeed;</l>
                  <l>Yet this condition was on her impos'd,</l>
                  <l>That it ſhould mortal prove, if ſhe diſclos'd</l>
                  <l>Her husbands counſels: who can now relate</l>
                  <l>The joy that ſhe conceiv'd to propagate</l>
                  <l>A divine birth? she reckons every day,</l>
                  <l>And week, and month, and does her womb ſurve,</l>
                  <l>And wonders ſince ſo little was inſtill'd,</l>
                  <l>So ſmall a veſſel ſhould ſo much be fill'd.</l>
                  <l>Her husband ſmelling of her ſiſters drift,</l>
                  <l>Began to call fair <hi>Pſiche</hi> unto ſhrift,</l>
                  <l>And warn her thus, The utmoſt day, ſays he,</l>
                  <l>And lateſt chance is now befalln to thee;</l>
                  <l>A ſex pernicious to thine own dear bloud</l>
                  <l>Has taken arms up to withſtand thy good.</l>
                  <l>Again thy ſiſters with regardleſs care</l>
                  <l>Of love, or piety, come to enſnare,</l>
                  <l>And tempt thy faith, which I forbad before,</l>
                  <l>That thou my ſhape and viſage ſhouldſt explore:</l>
                  <l>In lieu of which take up a like defence,</l>
                  <l>Protecting with religious continence</l>
                  <l>Our houſe from ruine, and thy ſelf prevent,</l>
                  <l>And our ſmall pledge from dangers imminent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> with ſighs and tears together blent,</l>
                  <l>Breaks off his ſpeech, Since you a document</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44380:16"/>
                  <l>Have of my ſilence and my love, quoth ſhe,</l>
                  <l>VVhy ſhould you fear to truſt my conſtancie:</l>
                  <l>Which to confirm, bid <hi>Zephirus</hi> fulfil</l>
                  <l>Once more his duty, and obey my will.</l>
                  <l>That ſince your long'd for ſight I am deni'd,</l>
                  <l>I may behold my ſiſters by my ſide.</l>
                  <l>Turn not away my love, I thee beſeek,</l>
                  <l>By thy curl'd hair, and by thy ſilken cheek:</l>
                  <l>Deign from thy bounty this ſmall boon to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Since the forc'd ignorance of what you are,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not offend me, nor the darkeſt night,</l>
                  <l>VVhere I embrace you in a greater light.</l>
                  <l>Charm'd with her ſugar'd words, he gives conſent,</l>
                  <l>That the ſwift wind with haſte incontinent,</l>
                  <l>Although unwilling, ſhould diſplay his wing,</l>
                  <l>And the ſhe-traitors to fair <hi>Pſiche</hi> bring.</l>
                  <l>Thus altogether met, her ſiſters twain</l>
                  <l>Embrace their prey, and a falſe love do feign.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche,</hi> ſays one, you are a mother grown,</l>
                  <l>Me-thinks your womb like a full Roſe is blown.</l>
                  <l>O what a maſs of comfort will accrue</l>
                  <l>Unto our friends and family from you?</l>
                  <l>Certs this your child, if it be half ſo fair</l>
                  <l>As is the mother, muſt be <hi>Cupid</hi>'s heir,</l>
                  <l>Thus they with flatteries and with many a ſmile,</l>
                  <l>Pretending falſe affection, her beguile;</l>
                  <l>And ſhe out of her innocence, poor Maid,</l>
                  <l>Gave eaſie credit unto all they ſaid;</l>
                  <l>And too too kind, to a fair chamber led,</l>
                  <l>VVhere with celeſtial dainties ſhe them fed.</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44380:17"/>
                  <l>She ſpeaks unto the Lute, and ſtraight it hears;</l>
                  <l>She calls for raptures, and they ſwell their ears.</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of Muſick ſound, with many a lay,</l>
                  <l>Yet none was preſent ſeen to ſing or play.</l>
                  <l>But as no mirth is pleaſant to a dull</l>
                  <l>And heavy ſoul, no leſs, they that are full</l>
                  <l>Of cankred malice, all delight diſdain,</l>
                  <l>But what doth nouriſh their delighted pain.</l>
                  <l>So that no gifts nor price might mollifie,</l>
                  <l>Nor no reward nor kindneſs qualifie</l>
                  <l>Their hardned hearts, ſtill they are on fire,</l>
                  <l>To ſound her through, and make a ſtrict inquire</l>
                  <l>What was her husband, what his form, and age,</l>
                  <l>And whence he did deduce his parentage:</l>
                  <l>You read, how from ſimplicity at firſt</l>
                  <l>She feign'd a formal ſtory, and what erſt</l>
                  <l>She told, ſhe had forgot, and 'gan to feign</l>
                  <l>Another rale, and of another ſtrain;</l>
                  <l>How that he was a man both rich and wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Of middle years, and of a middle ſize:</l>
                  <l>A Merchant by profeſſion, that did deal</l>
                  <l>For many thouſands in the Common-weal.</l>
                  <l>With that they check'd her in the full career</l>
                  <l>Of her diſcourſe, ſays one, Nay, ſiſter dear,</l>
                  <l>Pray do not ſtrive thus to impoſe upon</l>
                  <l>Your loving friends, ſure this deſcription</l>
                  <l>Muſt to his perſon needs be contrary,</l>
                  <l>When in it ſelf your ſpeech does diſagree.</l>
                  <l>You lately boaſted he was young and fair;</l>
                  <l>What, does the ſoil or nature of the air</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44380:17"/>
                  <l>Bring age ſo ſoon? and that he us'd to range</l>
                  <l>About the woods, loe there's another change.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o you conceit ſo ignorantly of us,</l>
                  <l>We know not <hi>Tethis</hi> from <hi>Hippolitus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Green fields from ſeas, a billow from a hill,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſhes from beaſts? then we had little skill.</l>
                  <l>You much diſſemble, or you have forgot</l>
                  <l>His form, and function, or you know them not.</l>
                  <l>Then with the preſſure of her eyes, ſhe freed</l>
                  <l>One tear from priſon, and did thus proceed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> we grieve, and pitty you, that thus</l>
                  <l>Are grown ſo careleſs and incurious</l>
                  <l>Of what you ought to fear: you think your ſelf</l>
                  <l>Much happy in your husband, and your pelf,</l>
                  <l>But are deceived, for we that watch,</l>
                  <l>And at each opportunity do catch,</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie our doubts, for truth have found,</l>
                  <l>Both by his crawling footſteps on the ground,</l>
                  <l>And by report of neighbouring husbandmen,</l>
                  <l>That have eſpy'd him flying from his den.</l>
                  <l>When he to them moſt hideouſly has yell'd,</l>
                  <l>From his huge throat, with blood and poyſon ſwel'd,</l>
                  <l>That this your husband is of Serpent breed,</l>
                  <l>Either of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> or of <hi>Hydra</hi>'s ſeed.</l>
                  <l>Call but the <hi>Pythian</hi> Oracle to mind,</l>
                  <l>That you to ſuch hard deſtiny aſſign'd;</l>
                  <l>And think not all your art, or policy,</l>
                  <l>Can cancell his prophetical decree.</l>
                  <l>Let not his Monſters uſage for awhile,</l>
                  <l>Your ſoul of juſt ſuſpition beguile,</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44380:18"/>
                  <l>As that you ſtill ſhall live at ſuch high rare,</l>
                  <l>And that theſe happy days ſhall ne're have date.</l>
                  <l>Far be it, that my words should ill portend,</l>
                  <l>Yet truſt me, all theſe joys muſt have an end:</l>
                  <l>The time will come, when this your Paramour,</l>
                  <l>In whom you ſo delight, shall you devour.</l>
                  <l>And when your womb caſts her abortive brood,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Saturn</hi> like, he will make that his food.</l>
                  <l>For this prediction alſo bore a share,</l>
                  <l>In what the god fore-told, but leſt deſpair</l>
                  <l>Should load you with too great oppreſſion,</l>
                  <l>It was conceal'd, and therefore ſtands upon,</l>
                  <l>Whether through our advice, you will be ſav'd,</l>
                  <l>Or in his beaſtly entrailes be engrav'd.</l>
                  <l>Now if this uncouth life, and ſolitude</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe you, then follow it, and be ſtill ſtew'd</l>
                  <l>In the rank luſt of a laſcivious worme:</l>
                  <l>Yet we our pious duties shall performe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſyche</hi> that tender was, grew wan, and pale,</l>
                  <l>And ſwoon for dread of this ſo ſad a tale.</l>
                  <l>Then fell she from the ſphear of her right mind,</l>
                  <l>And forgot all thoſe precepts she combin'd,</l>
                  <l>And vow'd to keep, and her ſelf headlong threw</l>
                  <l>Into a thouſand griefs, that muſt enſue.</l>
                  <l>At laſt reviv'd, having her ſelf upheav'd,</l>
                  <l>With fainting voice, thus half her words out breath'd</l>
                  <l>Truly my ſiſters dear, full well I ſee</l>
                  <l>How you perſiſt in conſtant piety:</l>
                  <l>Nor did they, who ſuggeſt ſuch words as theſe,</l>
                  <l>In my opinion altogether leaſe:</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:44380:18"/>
                  <l>For to this hour, I never did ſurvay</l>
                  <l>My husband's shape, but forc'd am to obay</l>
                  <l>What he commands, do embrace i'th night,</l>
                  <l>A thing uncertain, and that shuns the light:</l>
                  <l>Therefore to your aſſertions I aſſent,</l>
                  <l>That with good reaſon ſeem ſo congruent;</l>
                  <l>For in my thoughts I cannot judge at leaſt</l>
                  <l>But he muſt be a monſter, or ſome beaſt,</l>
                  <l>He uſes ſo much cautionary care,</l>
                  <l>And threatens ſo much ill, if I should dare</l>
                  <l>To view his face; ſo I referre me to</l>
                  <l>Your beſt advice, t' inſtruct me what to do:</l>
                  <l>Her ſiſters now arriv'd at the full ſcope</l>
                  <l>Of their baſe plots, and ſeeing the gate ope</l>
                  <l>That kept her heart, ſcorn any artfull bait,</l>
                  <l>But uſe their down-right weapons of deceit:</l>
                  <l>Saying, dear <hi>Pſiche,</hi> nature should prevail</l>
                  <l>So much with us, if miſchief did aſſail</l>
                  <l>Your perſon, in our ſight: we were too blame</l>
                  <l>Should we permit, and not divert the ſame;</l>
                  <l>Yet wiſe men have their ways, and eyes ſtill clear,</l>
                  <l>And leave no miſts of danger, or of fear:</l>
                  <l>You do but brave your death, when you repell</l>
                  <l>The whiſpers of your Genius, which would tell</l>
                  <l>The peril you re in; nor are you ſure</l>
                  <l>Of longer life, till you are quite ſecure:</l>
                  <l>Which to effect, provide a ſword that's keen,</l>
                  <l>And with it, a bright Lamp, and both unſeen</l>
                  <l>Hide in ſome place, untill a fitting hour</l>
                  <l>Shall call them, to aſſiſt you with their power:</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:44380:19"/>
                  <l>Truſt me, ſuch ſpies, and counſellors are mure,</l>
                  <l>And never nice, or ſlow to execute</l>
                  <l>Any deſign, ſo when your husbands eyes</l>
                  <l>Are ſeal'd with ſleep, from your ſoft couch ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſeiſe this Dragon, when he leaſt takes heed,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Pallas</hi> arm'd, and to his death proceed;</l>
                  <l>And where his neck, and head, are joyn'd in one,</l>
                  <l>Make me a ſpeedy ſeparation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alcides</hi> Son of <hi>Jove,</hi> as rumour goes,</l>
                  <l>Strangled two <hi>Serpents</hi> in his ſwadling cloaths:</l>
                  <l>And can your ſtrength fail to bring that to paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Which half the labour of an infant was?</l>
                  <l>Such wicked words they pour into her ear,</l>
                  <l>More poiſonous than her husband could appear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> was troubled, as the ſea, in wind</l>
                  <l>Approv'd their counſel, and again declin'd</l>
                  <l>What they perſwade; now haſtens, now delays,</l>
                  <l>Dares, and not dares, and with a bluſh betrays,</l>
                  <l>Her wandring paſſion, which knows no mean,</l>
                  <l>But travels from extream, unto extream:</l>
                  <l>She loves him now, and does again deteſt,</l>
                  <l>Loves as a husband, hates him as a beaſt.</l>
                  <l>The only check, and bridle to her hate,</l>
                  <l>Was the fam'd ſtory, and revengeful fate</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Danans</hi> Daughters, who in hell are bound</l>
                  <l>To fill a Veſſel, they can never ſound:</l>
                  <l>She told the ſtory to them, how all theſe</l>
                  <l>Were fifty Virgins, call'd the <hi>Belides;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her Sifters lift; while <hi>Pſiche</hi> does diſcover,</l>
                  <l>How each was too inhumane to her lover:</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:44380:19"/>
                  <l>And in on night made all their husbands-bleed;</l>
                  <l>With hearts, hard as the ſteel, that did the deed:</l>
                  <l>Yet one ſays ſhe, moſt worthy of the name</l>
                  <l>Of wife, and to it everlaſting fame:</l>
                  <l>Hight <hi>Hypermneſtra,</hi> with officious lye,</l>
                  <l>Met with her Father; and his perjury:</l>
                  <l>Who ſaid unto her husband, youth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt a long ſleep unfear'd, do thee ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>I will not hold thee captive, nor will ſtrike</l>
                  <l>This to thy heart; altough my ſiſters, like</l>
                  <l>So many cruell <hi>Lioneſſes,</hi> void</l>
                  <l>Of mercy, all their husbands have deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>I am of nature ſoft, nor do I dare</l>
                  <l>To view, much leſs to act my maſſacre;</l>
                  <l>What though my Father me in priſon lay,</l>
                  <l>Or load with Iron chains, or ſend away</l>
                  <l>Far from his Kingdome, into baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Or tortures uſe, cauſe I would not conſent</l>
                  <l>To murder thee; however take thy flight,</l>
                  <l>Poſt for thy life, whilſt <hi>Venus</hi> and the night</l>
                  <l>Do favour thee, and only this vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>When I am dead, to write my Epitaph:</l>
                  <l>The meer remembrance of this vertuous deed,</l>
                  <l>Did a remorce, and kind of pity breed</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pſiche</hi>'s breſt, for paſſions are infus'd,</l>
                  <l>According to the ſtories, we are us'd</l>
                  <l>To read; and many men do amorous prove,</l>
                  <l>By viewing acts, and monuments of love:</l>
                  <l>But yet her Siſters malice, that ſtill ſtood</l>
                  <l>In oppoſition, againſt all that's good,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:44380:20"/>
                  <l>Ceaſes not to precipiate her on,</l>
                  <l>Till they had gain'd this confirmation;</l>
                  <l>To put in act what ere they did deſire,</l>
                  <l>Thus fury like, they did her ſoul inſpire:</l>
                  <l>Night and her husband came, and now the ſport</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Venus</hi> ended, he began to ſnort,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche,</hi> though weak of mind, and body both,</l>
                  <l>Yet urg'd by cruell fate, and her raſh oath,</l>
                  <l>Roſe up to make proviſion for her ſin;</l>
                  <l>Lye ſtill fair maid, thou mayeſt more honour win,</l>
                  <l>And make thy murder glory, not a crime;</l>
                  <l>If thou wouldſt kill thoſe thoughts, that do beſlime</l>
                  <l>And knaw upon thy breaſt, and never ceaſe</l>
                  <l>With hiſhing clamours to diſturbe thy peace,</l>
                  <l>When thine own heart with <hi>Serpents</hi> doth abound;</l>
                  <l>Seek not without, that may within be found.</l>
                  <l>Yet was she not ſo cruell in her haſt,</l>
                  <l>But ere she kild him, she his lips would taſt,</l>
                  <l>Wishing she need not riſe out from her bed,</l>
                  <l>But that she had the power to kiſſe him dead:</l>
                  <l>Now with her lips she labours all she may,</l>
                  <l>To ſuck his ſoul out, whilſt he ſleeping lay,</l>
                  <l>Tih she at laſt through a transfuſed kiſs,</l>
                  <l>Left her own ſoul, and was inſpir'd by his;</l>
                  <l>And had her ſoul within his body ſtay'd,</l>
                  <l>Till he therein his vertues had convay'd,</l>
                  <l>And all pollution would from thence remove,</l>
                  <l>Then after all her thoughts had been of love;</l>
                  <l>Bur ſince she could not both of them retain,</l>
                  <l>She reſtor'd his, and took her own again:</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44380:20"/>
                  <l>Sorry, that ſhe was forc'd it to transfer,</l>
                  <l>And wiſht though dead, that he might live in her:</l>
                  <l>Then in one hand ſhe held the emulous light,</l>
                  <l>And in the other took the ſword, ſo bright</l>
                  <l>As 'twould her beauty, and the fire out-ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe thus arm'd, became more maſculine.</l>
                  <l>But when by friendſhip of the Lamp, her eye</l>
                  <l>Had made a perfect true diſcovery</l>
                  <l>Of all was in the room, what did ſhe ſee?</l>
                  <l>Object of Love, wonder of Deity.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>god of love</hi> himſelf, <hi>Cupid</hi> the fair.</l>
                  <l>Lye ſweetly ſleeping in his golden hair:</l>
                  <l>At this ſo heavenly ſight, the lampy ſpire</l>
                  <l>Encreas'd his flames, and burnt more pure, and higher.</l>
                  <l>The very ſenceleſs ſacrilegious ſteel,</l>
                  <l>Did a ſtrong vertue from his preſence feel,</l>
                  <l>Which turn'd the edge, poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> all amaz'd,</l>
                  <l>With joy, and wonder on his beauty gaz'd.</l>
                  <l>His neck ſo white, his colour ſo exact,</l>
                  <l>His limbes, that were ſo curiouſly compact:</l>
                  <l>His body ſleck, and ſmooth, that it might not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> repent, t' have ſuch a Son begot.</l>
                  <l>A bright reflection and pefumed ſent,</l>
                  <l>Fill'd all the room with a mixt blandiſhment,</l>
                  <l>Shot from his wings, and at his feet did lye</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Bow,</hi> and <hi>Arrows,</hi> and his <hi>Armory.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in this extaſie ſhe thought to hide</l>
                  <l>The curſed ſteel, but in her own dear ſide;</l>
                  <l>And had perform'd it ſure, had not the ſword,</l>
                  <l>Flew from her her hand, out of its own accord.</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:44380:21"/>
                  <l>Glanſing on all with eyes unſatisfied,</l>
                  <l>At laſt ſhe his artillery eſpyed.</l>
                  <l>The Quiver was of Needle-work wrought round</l>
                  <l>With trophies of his own, where <hi>Cupid</hi> crown'd.</l>
                  <l>Sate in the midſt, with a Bay-wreath, which he</l>
                  <l>Had proudly pluckt from the <hi>Peneian</hi> tree.</l>
                  <l>Next <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis,</hi> ſad with pain,</l>
                  <l>The one of <hi>love,</hi> the other of <hi>diſdain:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There <hi>Jove</hi> in all his borrowed ſhapes was dreſt,</l>
                  <l>His theſts, and his adulteries expreſt,</l>
                  <l>As Emblems of <hi>Loves</hi> triumph; and theſe were</l>
                  <l>Drawn with ſuch lively colours, men would ſwear,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Laeda</hi> lay within a perfect bower,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Danaes</hi> golden ſtreams, were a true ſhower.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturns</hi> two other Sons did ſeem to throw</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Tridents</hi> at his feet, and him allow</l>
                  <l>For their Supreme; and there were kneeling by</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gods, Nymphs,</hi> and all their Geneology</l>
                  <l>Since the firſt <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſaving the abuſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cupids</hi> pride, none could the work traduce.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallas</hi> in envy of <hi>Araeknes</hi> skill,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe to curry favour and fulfill</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupids</hi> beheſt, which ſhe durſt not withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Had fram'd the emulous piece with her own hand.</l>
                  <l>And there were portray'd more a thouſand loves</l>
                  <l>Beſides himself; the skins of Turtle-doves</l>
                  <l>Lin'd it within, and at the upper end,</l>
                  <l>A ſilver plate the Quiver did extend,</l>
                  <l>I all of ſmall holes, where his bright ſhafts did lye;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe plumes were ſtiff of gums of <hi>Araby.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44380:21"/>
                  <l>His Bow was of the beſt, and fineſt Yew</l>
                  <l>That in all <hi>Ida,</hi> or fair <hi>Tempe</hi> grew:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mooth as his cheek, and checkerd as his wing,</l>
                  <l>And at each end, tipt with a Pear; the ſtring</l>
                  <l>Drawn from the Optick of a Ladies eye,</l>
                  <l>That whenſoere he shoots, ſtrikes harmony.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſiche</hi> with timorous heed, did ſoftly touch</l>
                  <l>His weapons, leaſt her prophane hand might ſmutch</l>
                  <l>The gloſs of them: then drew a shaft, whoſe head</l>
                  <l>Was wrought of Gold, for ſome are done with Lead,</l>
                  <l>And laid her fingers end upon the Dart,</l>
                  <l>Tempting the edge, until it caus'd to ſmart:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or being poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted sharp, it raz'd the skin,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill drops of blood did trickle from within,</l>
                  <l>he wounded with the poiſon, which it bore,</l>
                  <l>Grew more in love, than ere she was before.</l>
                  <l>Then as she would her ſelf incorporate,</l>
                  <l>he did her numerous kiſſes equal make</l>
                  <l>Into his hairs, that with her breath did play,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teept with rich <hi>Nectar,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hus being ravisht with exceſs of joy,</l>
                  <l>With kiſſing, and embracing the ſweet Boy.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe, in the height of all her jollity,</l>
                  <l>Whether from envy, or from treachery:</l>
                  <l>Or that it had a burning appetite,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o touch that ſilken skin, that lookt ſo white.</l>
                  <l>The wicked Lamb in an unlucky hour,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> drop of ſcalding oil did let down poure</l>
                  <l>On his right shoulder, whence in horrid wiſe</l>
                  <l>A bliſter, like a bubble did ariſe,</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44380:22"/>
                  <l>And boil'd up in his fleſh, with a worſe fume,</l>
                  <l>Than blood of Vipers, or the <hi>Lernean</hi> ſpume.</l>
                  <l>Neer die the Dog-ſtar rage with ſo great heat</l>
                  <l>In dry <hi>Apuliae,</hi> nor <hi>Alcides</hi> ſweat</l>
                  <l>Under his ſhirt ſo. Cruell oil, that thou</l>
                  <l>Who of all others haſt the ſmootheſt brow,</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt play the traitor? who had any thing</l>
                  <l>Worſe than my ſelf, as fire, or venom'd ſting,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Sulphur</hi> blaſted him, ſhouldſt firſt have came,</l>
                  <l>And with thy powerful breath ſuckt out the flame.</l>
                  <l>For though he be <hi>Loves god,</hi> it were but vain,</l>
                  <l>To think he ſhould be priviledge from pain.</l>
                  <l>For we in <hi>Homer</hi> have like wounded read,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> both by <hi>Diomed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But for this hainous and audacious fact,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> among his ſtatutes did enact,</l>
                  <l>Henceforth all lights be baniſht, and exempt,</l>
                  <l>From bearing office in <hi>Loves</hi> government.</l>
                  <l>And in the day each ſhould his paſſage mark,</l>
                  <l>Or learn to find his Miſtreſs in the dark.</l>
                  <l>Sure all the crew of lovers ſhall thee hate,</l>
                  <l>Nor bleſt <hi>Minerva</hi> hold thee conſecrate.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Cupid</hi> ſaw his counſells open laid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiches</hi> dear faith, and his own plots betray'd,</l>
                  <l>He buckled on his wings, away to fly;</l>
                  <l>And had ſhe not caught hold upon his thigh,</l>
                  <l>And hung as an <hi>appendix</hi> of his flight,</l>
                  <l>He queſtionleſs had vaniſht from her ſight.</l>
                  <l>But as when men are in deep rivers drown'd,</l>
                  <l>And tane up dead, have their cloſe fingers found,</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:44380:22"/>
                  <l>Claſping the weeds; ſo, though her armes were rack.</l>
                  <l>With her more bodies weight, and ſinews crackt;</l>
                  <l>To follow him through the forc'd Element:</l>
                  <l>Yet held ſhe faſt, untill he did relent,</l>
                  <l>And his ambitious wings gan downward ſteer,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoop to earth, with a mild Cancileer.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>The fourth Section.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THus lighted on the earth, he took her wriſt,</l>
                  <l>And wrung it hard, and did her hands untwil</l>
                  <l>And having freed himſelf, he flew on high,</l>
                  <l>Unto a <hi>Cypreſs-tree,</hi> that grew thereby,</l>
                  <l>And on the utmoſt branches being ſate,</l>
                  <l>He did the matter thus capitulate,</l>
                  <l>Was it for this indeed, for this reward,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſilly girl, that I ſhould diſregard,</l>
                  <l>My mothers vows, her tears, her flatteries?</l>
                  <l>When ſhe, with all the power ſhe might ceviſe,</l>
                  <l>Provok't me to thy hurt, and thee aſſign'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Marriage, to a groom of ſome baſe kind,</l>
                  <l>And loweſt rank, had not my too much haſt</l>
                  <l>Redeem'd thy ſhame, and my own worth diſgrac'd;</l>
                  <l>Was it for this I did thy plagues remove,</l>
                  <l>To pain my ſelf? ſtrike mine own heart in love,</l>
                  <l>With mine own ſhaft, that after all this gear,</l>
                  <l>ſhould no better than a beaſt appear?</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or this, wouldſt thou cut off my head, which bore</l>
                  <l>Thoſe eyes, that did thy beauty ſo adore?</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd yet thou knowſt ungrateful wretch, how I</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id with my fears, thy miſchiefs ſtill imply,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44380:23"/>
                  <l>And every day my cautions did renew,</l>
                  <l>The breath of which thou muſt for ever rue:</l>
                  <l>And each of theſe thy ſiſters, that were guide</l>
                  <l>To thy ill act, ſhall dearly it abide:</l>
                  <l>Yet will I puniſh thee no other way</l>
                  <l>But only this, I will forever ſtray</l>
                  <l>Far from thy ſight, and having ſaid ſo, fled,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſhe to hear this news, lay almoſt dead:</l>
                  <l>Ye proſtrate on the ground, her eyes up caſt,</l>
                  <l>Ty'cto his winged ſpeed; until at laſt,</l>
                  <l>She could no more diſcern; as <hi>Dido,</hi> then,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Arudne,</hi> by ſome Poets pen,</l>
                  <l>Are faind to grieve; whoſe artful paſſions flow</l>
                  <l>In ſuch ſveet numbers, as they make their woe</l>
                  <l>Appear delightful, telling how unkind</l>
                  <l>Their loves ſtole away, and the ſame wind,</l>
                  <l>That blew abroad their faith, and oaths before,</l>
                  <l>Then fill'd their ſails, and how the troubled ſhore</l>
                  <l>Anſwer'd the Ladies groans, ſo <hi>Pſiche</hi> faints,</l>
                  <l>And bears her breaſt with pittiful complaints.</l>
                  <l>There ran a River near, whoſe purling ſtreams,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hyperion</hi> oft, did with his golden beams</l>
                  <l>Delight to gild, and as it fled along</l>
                  <l>The pleaſant murmurs, mixt with the ſweet ſong</l>
                  <l>Of aged <hi>Swans,</hi> detain'd the frequent ear</l>
                  <l>Of many a Nymph, which did inhabit there:</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> thither went, and from the brim,</l>
                  <l>In ſad deſpair threw her ſelf headlong in.</l>
                  <l>The Rivers God; whither 'twere out of fear,</l>
                  <l>Duty, or love, or honour he did bear</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44380:23"/>
                  <l>Her husband; or leaſt her ſpilt blood ſhould ſtain</l>
                  <l>His chriſtal current, threw her up again:</l>
                  <l>But it is thought, he would not let her ſink,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe <hi>Cupid</hi> oft times would deſcend to drink,</l>
                  <l>Or waſh him in the Brook, and when he came</l>
                  <l>To cool his own heat, would the floud inflame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pan</hi> at that time ſat playing on a reed,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt his rough <hi>Goats</hi> did on the medows feed,</l>
                  <l>And with intentive eyes obſerved all,</l>
                  <l>That to the faireſt <hi>Pſiche</hi> did befall;</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeing her thus pitiouſly diſtreſt,</l>
                  <l>He ran to take her up, and did the beſt</l>
                  <l>He could to comfort her; fair maid, ſays he,</l>
                  <l>Though a ruſtick, and a ſhepheard be,</l>
                  <l>Scorn not for that my counſel, and advice;</l>
                  <l>Nor let my trade become my prejudice.</l>
                  <l>For by the benefit of time well ſpent,</l>
                  <l>I am indued with long experiment:</l>
                  <l>And if I do conjecture it aright,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe of all this Phrenſie, and diſpight,</l>
                  <l>Which your ſad looks, and paleneſs do imply,</l>
                  <l>With other ſigns in Phyſiognomy,</l>
                  <l>By which wiſe men the truth of <hi>Art</hi> do prove,</l>
                  <l>And know the ſtate of minds; you are in love.</l>
                  <l>Now liſt to me, and do not with fond haſt</l>
                  <l>The ſacred oil of your lifes taper waſt:</l>
                  <l>Uſe no ſiniſter means, to haſten on,</l>
                  <l>But labour to adjourn deſtruction,</l>
                  <l>Caſt not away your ſelf by too much grief,</l>
                  <l>But courage take; for care is beauties thief:</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:44380:24"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> I know, whoſe humour is to ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>Then yield, then ſtay, then play the fugitive.</l>
                  <l>Be not diſmay'd for that, but ſhew your duty,</l>
                  <l>And above all things do not ſpoil your beauty,</l>
                  <l>He's delicate, and wanton, prayers may win,</l>
                  <l>And fair demeanour may demerit him.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the medicines I would have you chuſe,</l>
                  <l>To cure your minds health, and redreſs abuſe:</l>
                  <l>She gave him thanks, then roſe from where ſhe lay,</l>
                  <l>And having done obeyſance went her way;</l>
                  <l>Thence did ſhe wander on with weary feet,</l>
                  <l>And neither track, nor paſſenger could meet,</l>
                  <l>Untill at length ſhe found a Kingly road</l>
                  <l>Which led unto a Palace, where aboad</l>
                  <l>Her eldeſt ſiſter. <hi>Pſiche</hi> enter'd in,</l>
                  <l>Thent ſent up news, how one of her near kin,</l>
                  <l>Was come to viſit her, return being made,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> was brought before her, each invade</l>
                  <l>The other with embraces, and fulfill</l>
                  <l>A tedious ſcene of counterfeit good will.</l>
                  <l>But when they had diſcours'd a while together,</l>
                  <l>She askt <hi>Pſiche</hi> the cauſe, that brought her thither,</l>
                  <l>Who did recount the paſſages, and tell,</l>
                  <l>In order all the ſtory that befell,</l>
                  <l>Which by degrees had ruin'd her, and laid</l>
                  <l>The blame on their lewd counſell, that betray'd</l>
                  <l>Her innocent ſoul, and her firm faith miſled,</l>
                  <l>To murder her dear husband in his bed:</l>
                  <l>She told how ſhe his certain death decreed,</l>
                  <l>And how ſhe roſe to execute the deed:</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:44380:24"/>
                  <l>She told, how like a <hi>Lionneſs</hi> ſhe far'd,</l>
                  <l>And like an armed fury, how ſhe ſtar'd;</l>
                  <l>Or like a blazing comet in the aire,</l>
                  <l>With fire, and ſword, and with diſ-ſhevell'd hair,</l>
                  <l>She told the trouble, and Epitaſis,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe beheld his Metamorphoſis:</l>
                  <l>A ſpectacle, that raviſht her with joy,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Serpent</hi> turn'd into a lovely boy,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe young, ſmooth face, migh't ſpeak him boy or maid:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> himſelf in a ſoft ſlumber layd;</l>
                  <l>She told too of the drop of ſcalding oil,</l>
                  <l>That burnt his ſhoulder, and the heavy coil</l>
                  <l>He kept, when he awak't, caus'd by the ſmart;</l>
                  <l>And how he chid, and how at laſt did part:</l>
                  <l>And for revenge, had threatned in her ſtead,</l>
                  <l>To maſte her ſiſters partners of his bed,</l>
                  <l>And 'twixt each word, she let a tear down fall,</l>
                  <l>Which ſtopt her voice, and made it muſicall.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Pſiche</hi> at the laſt, finisht her ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Seaſon'd with sharp grief, and ſweet oratory,</l>
                  <l>Which was as long by her relation made,</l>
                  <l>As might have ſerv'd to ſtuffe an <hi>Iliade.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such as <hi>Aeneas</hi> unto <hi>Dido</hi> told,</l>
                  <l>Full of adventures, ſtrange, and manifold.</l>
                  <l>Her ſiſter by her looks great joy did show,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd in that, she did her husband know;</l>
                  <l>And therefore heard her out, with much applauſe,</l>
                  <l>And gave great heed, but chiefly to that clauſe</l>
                  <l>Where 'twas declar'd, that he her pomp and ſtate</l>
                  <l>To one of her own ſiſters would tranſlate.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:44380:25"/>
                  <l>VVhence gathering that her ſelf might be his Bride,</l>
                  <l>She ſwell'd with luſt, with envy and with pride;</l>
                  <l>And in this heat of paſſion did tranſcend</l>
                  <l>The Rock, where <hi>Zephirus</hi> us'd to attend</l>
                  <l>To waft her up and down, and there call'd on</l>
                  <l>Him, that had now forſook his ſtation.</l>
                  <l>Yet through the vanity of hope made blind,</l>
                  <l>Though then there blew a contrary wind:</l>
                  <l>Invoking <hi>Cupid</hi> that he would receive</l>
                  <l>Her for his Spouſe, ſhe did her ſelf bequeath</l>
                  <l>Unto a fearful precipice, and threw</l>
                  <l>Her body head-long down, whoſe weight it drew</l>
                  <l>Towards the centre; for without ſupport,</l>
                  <l>All heavy matter thither will reſort.</l>
                  <l>In this her fall, the hard ſtones by the way</l>
                  <l>Did greet her limbs with a diſcourteous ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Bruiſing her in that manner that ſhe di'd,</l>
                  <l>As if that ſhe her Jury had deni'd.</l>
                  <l>Her younger ſiſter miſſing thus the chief</l>
                  <l>Co-partner of her ſorrows, pin'd for grief.</l>
                  <l>This craggy rock did over look the ſea,</l>
                  <l>Where greedy <hi>Neptune</hi> had are in a Bay,</l>
                  <l>And undermining it much ground did win,</l>
                  <l>VVhere ſilver-footed <hi>Thetis</hi> riding in</l>
                  <l>Upon a bridled Dolphin, did explore,</l>
                  <l>And every tyde her arms ſtretch'd on the ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Searching each creek and crany to augment</l>
                  <l>The confines of her watry regiment.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt here ſhe ſate within a peerly chair,</l>
                  <l>And round her all the <hi>Sea-gods</hi> did repair;</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44380:25"/>
                  <l>To whom her Laws ſhe did preſcribe by hap,</l>
                  <l>The mangled corps fell full into her lap.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thetis,</hi> that once a child her ſelf had born,</l>
                  <l>Seeing ſo fair a body fouly torn,</l>
                  <l>And bleeding freſh, judging ſome raviſher</l>
                  <l>Had done this injury, ſhe did confer</l>
                  <l>About the cure, and there were many found</l>
                  <l>Whoſe trade in Surgery could heal a wound,</l>
                  <l>But none that might reſtore to life agen.</l>
                  <l>Such was the envy of the gods: for when</l>
                  <l>The scatter'd limbs of chaſt <hi>Hippolitus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were re-inſpir'd by <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by his <hi>Arts</hi> command together came,</l>
                  <l>And every bone and joynt put into frame:</l>
                  <l>That none with emulous skill ſhould dare the like,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove</hi> him to hell did with his thunder ſtrike.</l>
                  <l>But though ſhe could not by her power controle</l>
                  <l>The fates decree, to reunite the ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Into another ſhape ſhe made it paſs,</l>
                  <l>A doctrin held by old <hi>Pythagoras:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſtripping off her clothes, ſhe made her skin</l>
                  <l>To wear a ſoft and plumy coverin.</l>
                  <l>Her griſly noſe was hardned to a bill,</l>
                  <l>And at each fingers end grew many a quill.</l>
                  <l>Her arms to pennons turn'd, and ſhe in all</l>
                  <l>Chang'd to a Foul, which men a <hi>Sea-gull</hi> call;</l>
                  <l>A Bird of evil nature, and ſet on</l>
                  <l>Much miſchief, to whoſe compoſition</l>
                  <l>A great part of her former malice went,</l>
                  <l>And was the principal ingredient.</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:44380:26"/>
                  <l>For being thus transfigur'd, ſtraight ſhe ſwam</l>
                  <l>Into the bottom of the Ocean,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Neptune</hi> kept his Court, and preſſing near</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Venus</hi> ſeat, ſhe whiſper'd her i'th' ear,</l>
                  <l>How that her ſon lay deſperately griev'd,</l>
                  <l>Sick of a burn he lately had receiv'd:</l>
                  <l>And many by that means at her did ſcoff,</l>
                  <l>And her whole family was ill ſpoken of.</l>
                  <l>For whilſt that ſhe her ſelf thus liv'd recluſe,</l>
                  <l>And he his cloſe adulteries did uſe:</l>
                  <l>No ſport or pleaſure, no delight or grace,</l>
                  <l>Friendſhip or marriage could find any place.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Love</hi> no pledge, no harmony in life,</l>
                  <l>But every where confuſion was, and ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>Thus the vile Bird maliciouſly did prate,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cupid</hi>'s credit did calumniate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> repli'd, impatient and hot,</l>
                  <l>What, has my good ſon then a Miſtreſs got?</l>
                  <l>Which of the Nymphs or Muſes is his joy?</l>
                  <l>Who has inveigl'd the ingenious Boy?</l>
                  <l>Which of the Howers, or of the Graces all?</l>
                  <l>None of theſe, ſaid the Bird, but men her call</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche.</hi> So ſoon as <hi>Venus</hi> heard her nam'd,</l>
                  <l>O how with indignation ſhe exclaim'd?</l>
                  <l>VVhat, my own beauties rival, is it ſhe?</l>
                  <l>That plant, that ſucker of my dignity,</l>
                  <l>And I his Bawd? with theſe words ſhe aſcended</l>
                  <l>To the Seas <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> where attended</l>
                  <l>Her Doves both ready harneſs'd, up ſhe got,</l>
                  <l>And flew to <hi>Paphos</hi> in her chariot.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:44380:26"/>
                  <l>The graces came about her, and in haſte</l>
                  <l>VVhat the rough ſeas or rude winds had miſplac'd,</l>
                  <l>Did recompoſe with art and ſtudious care,</l>
                  <l>Kembing the cerule drops from her looſe hair,</l>
                  <l>Which dri'd with roſie powder, they did fold,</l>
                  <l>And bind it round up in a braid of gold.</l>
                  <l>Theſe wait about her perſon ſtill, and paſs</l>
                  <l>Their judgment on her, equal with her glaſs.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the onely <hi>Criticks</hi> that debate</l>
                  <l>All beauty, and all faſhions arbitrate:</l>
                  <l>Theſe temper her <hi>Ceruſe,</hi> and paint, and lim</l>
                  <l>Her face with oyl, and put her in her trim,</l>
                  <l>Twelve other Hand-maids clad in white array,</l>
                  <l>Call'd the <hi>twelve Hours,</hi> and <hi>daughters of the day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did help to dreſs her: there were added more,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Twelve of the night,</hi> whoſe eyes were ſhadowed o're</l>
                  <l>VVith dusky and black vails, leſt <hi>Vulcan</hi>'s light,</l>
                  <l>Or vapours ſhould offend their bleared ſight,</l>
                  <l>VVhen they her linnen ſtarch, or elſe prepare</l>
                  <l>Strong diſtillations to make her fair.</l>
                  <l>Theſe bring her bathes and oyntments for her eyes,</l>
                  <l>And provide Cordials 'gainſt ſhe ſhall riſe.</l>
                  <l>Theſe play on Muſick, and perfume her bed,</l>
                  <l>And ſnuff the candle while ſhe lies to read</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf aſleep: thus all aſſign'd unto</l>
                  <l>Their ſeveral office, had enough to do.</l>
                  <l>And had they twenty times as many been,</l>
                  <l>They all might be employ'd about the Queen.</l>
                  <l>For though they us'd more reverence then at prayer,</l>
                  <l>And ſate in counſel upon every hair,</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:44380:27"/>
                  <l>And every pleat and poſture of her gown,</l>
                  <l>Giving obſervance to each frequent frown;</l>
                  <l>And rather wish'd the State diſorder'd were,</l>
                  <l>Then the leaſt implement that ſhe did wear:</l>
                  <l>As if, of all, that were the greateſt ſin,</l>
                  <l>And that their fate were faſtned to each pin:</l>
                  <l>Though their whole life and ſtudy were to pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſuch a ſullen humour and diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>Reign'd in her curious eyes, ſhe ever ſaught,</l>
                  <l>And ſcouling look'd, where she might find a fault;</l>
                  <l>Yet felt she no diſtemper from the care</l>
                  <l>Of other buſineſs, nor did any dare</l>
                  <l>To interpoſe or put into her mine</l>
                  <l>A thought of any either foe or friend,</l>
                  <l>Receipt or payment, but they all were bent</l>
                  <l>To place each jewel and each ornament.</l>
                  <l>And when that she was dreſs'd, and all was done,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhe began to think upon her ſon,</l>
                  <l>And being abſent ſpake of him at large,</l>
                  <l>And laid ſtrong aggravations to his charge:</l>
                  <l>She ript her wrongs up, how she had paſs'd by,</l>
                  <l>In hope of mendment, many an injury;</l>
                  <l>Yet nothing could reclaim his ſtubborn ſplene,</l>
                  <l>And wanton looſneſs, though she ſtill had been</l>
                  <l>Indulgent to him, as they all did know.</l>
                  <l>She talk'd too of the duty children owe</l>
                  <l>Unto their parents, and did much complain,</l>
                  <l>Since she had bore and bred him up with pain,</l>
                  <l>Now for requital had receiv'd offence;</l>
                  <l>And ſorely tax'd his diſobedience.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:44380:27"/>
                  <l>Then ask'd the Graces if they could diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>Where his new hants were, and his Randezvouſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or she had truſted them to over-look,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s guardians, and to guide, as with a hook,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is ſtragling nature; and they had done ill</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſlack their hand, and leave him to his will;</l>
                  <l>Who, as ſhe ſaid, was a weak child, and none</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing near, might ſoon into much miſchief run.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey blushing ſmile, and thus alledge, Since she,</l>
                  <l>His mother could not rule him, how can we</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat are but ſervants? whom he does deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>nd brandishes his torch againſt our eyes,</l>
                  <l>And in defiance threats what he will do,</l>
                  <l>Upon the leaſt diſtaſte, to shoot us through.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> heard how the world ſtood in awe</l>
                  <l>Of her ſon's deſperate valour, and no Law</l>
                  <l>Might curb his fierceneſs, flattery nor force</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>revail, she then reſolv'd upon a courſe,</l>
                  <l>VVith open Libels, and with hue and cry,</l>
                  <l>To publish to the world his infamy:</l>
                  <l>And therefore caus'd in every town and ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>And in all trivial places where ways meet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n theſe words or the like, upon each poſte,</l>
                  <l>A chartel to be fix'd that he was loſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The wanton <hi>Cupid</hi> th'other day.</l>
                     <l>Did from his mother <hi>Venus</hi> ſtray.</l>
                     <l>Great pains ſhe took, but all in vain,</l>
                     <l>How to get her ſon again:</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:44380:28"/>
                     <l>For ſince the Boy is ſometimes blind,</l>
                     <l>He his own way cannot find.</l>
                     <l>If any one can fetch him in,</l>
                     <l>Or take him captive in a Gin,</l>
                     <l>And bring her word, ſhe for this</l>
                     <l>Will reward him with a kiſs.</l>
                     <l>That you the Felon may deſcry,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are ſigns to know him by:</l>
                     <l>His skin is red with many a stain</l>
                     <l>Of Lovers, which by him were ſlain;</l>
                     <l>Or elſe it is the fatal doom,</l>
                     <l>Which fore-tels of ſtorms to come:</l>
                     <l>Though he ſeem naked to the eye,</l>
                     <l>His mind is cloath'd with ſubtilty,</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſpeech he uſes, and ſoft ſmiles,</l>
                     <l>To intice where he beguiles:</l>
                     <l>His words are gentle as the air,</l>
                     <l>But truſt him not, though he ſpeak fair,</l>
                     <l>And confirm it with an oath:</l>
                     <l>He is fierce and cruel both:</l>
                     <l>He is bold and careleſs too,</l>
                     <l>And will play as wantons do:</l>
                     <l>But when you think the ſport is paſt,</l>
                     <l>It turns to earneſt at the laſt.</l>
                     <l>His evil nature none can tame,</l>
                     <l>For neither reverence nor ſhame</l>
                     <l>Are in his looks: his curled hair</l>
                     <l>Hangs like nets for to enſnare:</l>
                     <l>His hands, though weak and ſlender, strike</l>
                     <l>Age and ſexes all alike,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:44380:28"/>
                     <l>And when he liſt, will make his neſt</l>
                     <l>In their marrow or their breast:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe poiſon'd Darts ſhot from his Bow,</l>
                     <l>Hurt gods above, and men below.</l>
                     <l>His left hand bears a burning Torch,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe flame the very ſome will ſcorch;</l>
                     <l>And not hell it ſelf is free</l>
                     <l>From this Imps impiety.</l>
                     <l>The wounds he makes no ſalve can cure.</l>
                     <l>Then if you catch him, bind him ſure:</l>
                     <l>Take no pity, though he cry,</l>
                     <l>Or laugh, or ſmile, or ſeem to die,</l>
                     <l>And for his ranſome would deliver</l>
                     <l>His arrows and his painted quiver;</l>
                     <l>Refuſe them all, for they are ſuch</l>
                     <l>That will burn where e'r they touch.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <l>When this Edict was openly declar'd,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> importunity, none dar'd</l>
                  <l>To be ſo much of counſel as to hide,</l>
                  <l>And not reveal where <hi>Cupid</hi> did abide.</l>
                  <l>There was an old Nymph of th' <hi>Idalian</hi> grove,</l>
                  <l>Grand-child to <hi>Faune,</hi> a <hi>Dryade,</hi> whom great <hi>Jove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had raviſh'd in her youth, and for a fee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n recompence of her Virginity,</l>
                  <l>Did make immortal, and with wiſdom fill,</l>
                  <l>And her endow'd with a prophetick skill,</l>
                  <l>And knowledge of all herbs, ſhe could apply</l>
                  <l>To every grief a perfect remedy,</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:44380:29"/>
                  <l>Were it in mind, or body, and was ſage,</l>
                  <l>And waighty in her counſel, to aſwage</l>
                  <l>Any diſeaſe; ſhe had the government</l>
                  <l>Of the whole Pallace, and was preſident</l>
                  <l>Of all the Nimphs, for <hi>Venus</hi> did commit</l>
                  <l>Such power, to do; what ever ſhe thought fit.</l>
                  <l>She at that time dreſt <hi>Cupid</hi> for his ſmart,</l>
                  <l>And would have hid his ſhame with all her heart;</l>
                  <l>But that ſhe fear'd her Miſtreſs to diſpleaſe,</l>
                  <l>If it ſhould after chance the <hi>Driades</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betray'd her: therefore ſhe durſt do no other,</l>
                  <l>But to ſend private word unto his Mother,</l>
                  <l>Where her Son was, and how he hid his head,</l>
                  <l>And groaning lay upon his Mothers bed.</l>
                  <l>Soon as this news was brought her, <hi>Venus</hi> went,</l>
                  <l>Blown with the wind, and her own diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>And there began to ſcold, and rail, before</l>
                  <l>She did arrive within the Chamber door.</l>
                  <l>Are theſe things honeſt, which I hear, ſays ſhe,</l>
                  <l>And ſuiting with our fame, and pedegree?</l>
                  <l>Seducing triſſer, have you ſet at large,</l>
                  <l>Mine enemy, whom I gave up in charge,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſhouldſt captivate, and ſet on fire,</l>
                  <l>With fordid, but unquenchable deſire?</l>
                  <l>But ſince; that thou mightſt the more ſtubborn prove,</l>
                  <l>Haſt fetter'd her unto thy ſelf in love;</l>
                  <l>Seems you preſume, that you are only he,</l>
                  <l>The Chick of the white Hen, and ſtill muſt be.</l>
                  <l>And I, by reaſon of my age, quite done,</l>
                  <l>Cannot conceive, nor bear another Son.</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:44380:29"/>
                  <l>Yes know I can, and for thy more diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will adopt another in thy place.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l take away that wicked ſtuff, with which</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt abuſe thy betters, and bewitch</l>
                  <l>Each age and ſex, and not without delight,</l>
                  <l>Thine uncle <hi>Mars</hi> and thine own mother ſmite.</l>
                  <l>Then burn thoſe arms, which were ordain'd to do</l>
                  <l>Better exploits then thou imploy'ſt them to.</l>
                  <l>For thou waſt ever from thy youth unroward,</l>
                  <l>And doſt, without all reverence or regard,</l>
                  <l>Provoke thy elders; but, <hi>Jove,</hi> here I wiſh</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne'r may eat of a celeſtial diſh,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs I turn this triumph to offence,</l>
                  <l>This ſweet to four, this ſport to penitence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t I thus ſcorned, whether ſhall I flie?</l>
                  <l>There is a Matron call'd <hi>Sobriety,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom I have oft offended, through his vain</l>
                  <l>Luxurious riot, yet I muſt complain</l>
                  <l>To her, and at her hands expect the full</l>
                  <l>Of my revenge, ſhe ſhall his quiver pull,</l>
                  <l>Unhead his <hi>arrows,</hi> and his <hi>bow</hi> onſtring,</l>
                  <l>Put out his <hi>Torch,</hi> and then away it fling.</l>
                  <l>His golden locks with <hi>Nectar</hi> all imbrew'd,</l>
                  <l>Which I from mine own boſome have bedew'd.</l>
                  <l>His various wings the Rain-bow never yet</l>
                  <l>VVas in ſuch order nor ſuch colours ſet:</l>
                  <l>She ſhall without remorſe both cut and pare,</l>
                  <l>And every feather clip, and every hair.</l>
                  <l>And then, and not till then, it ſhall ſuffice</l>
                  <l>That I have done my wrongs this ſacrifice.</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:44380:30"/>
                  <l>Thus full of choler did she <hi>Cupid</hi> threat,</l>
                  <l>And having eas'd her mind did back retreat.</l>
                  <l>But making haſte, with this diſtemper'd look,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> both ſhe overtook:</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeing her with ſuch a troubled brow,</l>
                  <l>Did earneſtly demand the manner how</l>
                  <l>She came ſo vex'd, and who had power to ſhrowd</l>
                  <l>Her glorious beauty in ſo black a clowd.</l>
                  <l>You cannot chuſe but hear, <hi>Venus</hi> reply'd,</l>
                  <l>How I have been abus'd on every ſide:</l>
                  <l>Firſt, when my limping husband me beſet,</l>
                  <l>And caught <hi>Mars</hi> and my ſelf both in his net,</l>
                  <l>And then expos'd us naked to the eyes</l>
                  <l>Of heaven, and the whole bench of deities.</l>
                  <l>'Tis a known tale, and to make up the jeſt,</l>
                  <l>One <hi>god,</hi> leſs ſupercilious then the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Told <hi>Mars,</hi> if thoſe his fetters made him ſweat,</l>
                  <l>He would endure the burthen and the heat.</l>
                  <l>Time wore out this diſgrace, but now your art</l>
                  <l>Muſt drive another ſorrow from my heart:</l>
                  <l>And if you love me, uſe your beſt of skill</l>
                  <l>To ſeek out <hi>Pſiche,</hi> she hath done this ill:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> my ſon has choſe her for his ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>That is the onely plague unto my houſe.</l>
                  <l>Lady, ſaid they, alack, what hurt is done,</l>
                  <l>Or crime in this committed by your ſon?</l>
                  <l>Is this a cauſe fit to provoke your ſpight,</l>
                  <l>T' impugn his ſports and hinder his delight?</l>
                  <l>What imputation on your houſe were laid,</l>
                  <l>Though he ſhould ſet his fancy on a Maid?</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:44380:30"/>
                  <l>You may allow his patent for to paſs,</l>
                  <l>That he may love a blithe and bonny Laſs.</l>
                  <l>What, you forget that he is well in years,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis a comfort to you that he bears</l>
                  <l>His age ſo well; therefore you muſt not pry</l>
                  <l>Into his actions ſo narrowly.</l>
                  <l>For with what juſtice can you diſapprove</l>
                  <l>That in your ſon, which in your ſelf you love?</l>
                  <l>Is't fit that ſeeds of <hi>love</hi> by you be ſown</l>
                  <l>In others hearts, and banish'd from your own?</l>
                  <l>You have an intereſt in all that's his;</l>
                  <l>Both prais'd for good, both blam'd for what's amiſs.</l>
                  <l>Remember too you are his mother dear,</l>
                  <l>Held wiſe, and muſt give way. Thus they for fear</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Cupid</hi>'s arrows did him patronize.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Venus</hi> ſcorning that her injuries</l>
                  <l>Were no more pitied, her ſwift Doves did raign,</l>
                  <l>And took her way towards the Sea again.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt Book.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:44380:31"/>
            <head>The Second Book.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>THE FIRST SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PSiche</hi> this while wandred the world about</l>
                  <l>With various errors to find <hi>Cupid</hi> out,</l>
                  <l>Hoping, although no matrimonial way,</l>
                  <l>Or beauty's force his anger might allay,</l>
                  <l>Yet prayers and duty ſometimes do abate,</l>
                  <l>And humble ſervice him propitiate.</l>
                  <l>She travell'd forth, until at length ſhe found</l>
                  <l>A pleaſant plain, with a fair <hi>Temple</hi> crown'd;</l>
                  <l>Then to her ſelf ſhe ſaid, Ah, who can tell</l>
                  <l>Whether or no my husband there do dwell?</l>
                  <l>And with this thought ſhe goes directly on,</l>
                  <l>Led with blind hope and with devotion:</l>
                  <l>Then entring in, ſhe to the <hi>Altar</hi> bended,</l>
                  <l>And there perform'd her <hi>Orizons;</hi> which ended,</l>
                  <l>Caſting her eyes about, ſhe did eſpy</l>
                  <l>A world of inſtruments for husbandry,</l>
                  <l>As Forks, and Hooks, and Rakes, Sickles and Sithes,</l>
                  <l>Garlands, and Shears, and Corn for ſacrifice.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ears that were confuſed ſhe did ſever,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that ſcatter'd lay ſhe put together;</l>
                  <l>Thinking ſhe ought no worſhip to decline</l>
                  <l>Of any thing that ſeem'd to be divine.</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:44380:31"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceres</hi> far off did <hi>Pſiche</hi> over-look,</l>
                  <l>When this laborious task ſhe undertook;</l>
                  <l>And as ſhe is a <hi>goddeſs</hi> that does love</l>
                  <l>Induſtrious people, ſpake to her from above;</l>
                  <l>Alas, poor <hi>Pſiche, Venus</hi> is thy foe,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrives to find thee out with more ado</l>
                  <l>Then I my <hi>Proſerpine,</hi> the earth, the ſea,</l>
                  <l>And the hid confines of the night and day,</l>
                  <l>Have all been ranſack'd; ſhe has ſought thee forth</l>
                  <l>Through both the <hi>Poles</hi> and manſions of the North,</l>
                  <l>Not the <hi>Riphean</hi> ſnow, nor all the droughth</l>
                  <l>That parches the vaſt deſarts of the ſouth,</l>
                  <l>Have ſtaid her ſteps: ſhe has made <hi>Tethis</hi> ſweep,</l>
                  <l>To find thee out, the bottom of the deep,</l>
                  <l>And vows that heaven it ſelf shall thee reſign,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Jove</hi> had fix'd thee there his concubine.</l>
                  <l>She never reſts, for ſince she went to bed,</l>
                  <l>The roſie Crown is wither'd from her head.</l>
                  <l>Thou careleſs wretch, thus <hi>Venus</hi> all enrag'd,</l>
                  <l>Seeks for thy life, whilſt thou art here engag'd</l>
                  <l>Bout my affairs, and thinkſt of nothing leſs</l>
                  <l>Then thine own ſafety and loſt happineſs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> fell proſtrate on her face before</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Ceres</hi> throne, and did her help implore,</l>
                  <l>Moiſtning the earth with tears, and with her hair</l>
                  <l>Brushing the ground, she ſent up many a prayer:</l>
                  <l>By thy fruit-ſcattering hand I thee entreat,</l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Sicilian</hi> fields, that are the ſeat</l>
                  <l>Of thy fertility, and by the glad</l>
                  <l>And happy ends the harveſt ever had;</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44380:32"/>
                  <l>And by thy Coach, with winged <hi>Dragons</hi> drawn,</l>
                  <l>And by the darkſome hell that 'gan to dawn</l>
                  <l>At the bright marriage of fair <hi>Proſerpine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by the ſilent rites of <hi>Eluſine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Impart ſome pity, and vouchſafe to grant</l>
                  <l>This ſmall requeſt to your poor ſuppliant,</l>
                  <l>I may lie hid among theſe ſheaves of corn</l>
                  <l>Until great <hi>Venus</hi> fury be out-worn;</l>
                  <l>Or that my ſtrength and faculties ſubdu'd</l>
                  <l>By weary toil, a little be renew'd.</l>
                  <l>But as the world's accuſtom'd, when they ſee</l>
                  <l>Any o'rwhelm'd with a deep miſery,</l>
                  <l>Afford ſmall comfort to their wretched ſtate,</l>
                  <l>But onely are in words compaſſionate:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Ceres</hi> told her, ſhe did greatly grieve</l>
                  <l>At her diſtreſs, but durſt her not relieve;</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Venus</hi> was a good and gracious Queen,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe her favour highly did eſteem.</l>
                  <l>Nor would she ſuccour a contrary ſide,</l>
                  <l>Being by love and kin to her alli'd.</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> thus repuls'd, ſoon as she ſaw</l>
                  <l>Her hopes quite fruſtrate, did her ſelf with-draw,</l>
                  <l>And journeyed on unto a neighbouring wood,</l>
                  <l>Where likewiſe a rich <hi>Fane</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Of goodly ſtructure, and before the houſe</l>
                  <l>Hung many gifts and garments precious,</l>
                  <l>That by the name engrav'd, and dedication,</l>
                  <l>Expreſs'd without to whom they had relation.</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Pſiche</hi> enter'd, her low knees did bend,</l>
                  <l>And both her ſelf and fortunes recommend</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:44380:32"/>
                  <l>To mighty <hi>Juno,</hi> and thus ſpake to her,</l>
                  <l>Thou wife and ſiſter to the Thunderer,</l>
                  <l>Whether thou doſt in antient <hi>Samos</hi> lie,</l>
                  <l>The place of thy firſt birth and nurſery;</l>
                  <l>Or by the banks of <hi>Inacus</hi> abide,</l>
                  <l>Or thy lov'd <hi>Carthage,</hi> or round heaven doſt ride</l>
                  <l>Upon a <hi>Lion</hi>'s back; that art i'th' eaſt</l>
                  <l>Call'd <hi>Zigia,</hi> and <hi>Lucina</hi> in the weſt:</l>
                  <l>Look on my grief's extremity, and deign</l>
                  <l>To eaſe me of my labour and my pain.</l>
                  <l>Thus having pray'd, ſtreight <hi>Juno</hi> from on high</l>
                  <l>Preſents her ſelf in all her Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid, <hi>Pſiche,</hi> I wiſh you had your ends,</l>
                  <l>And that my daughter and your ſelf were friends:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Venus</hi> I have ever held moſt dear,</l>
                  <l>In as high place as she my daughter were:</l>
                  <l>Nor can that, which one <hi>goddeſs</hi> has begun,</l>
                  <l>By any other Deity b' undone:</l>
                  <l>Beſides the <hi>Stigian</hi> Laws allow no leave,</l>
                  <l>That we another's ſervant should receive;</l>
                  <l>Nor can we by the league of friendſhip give</l>
                  <l>Relief to one that is a fugitive.</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Pſiche</hi> shipwrack'd in her hopes again,</l>
                  <l>And finding no ways how she might obtain</l>
                  <l>Her winged husband, caſt the worſt of all,</l>
                  <l>And thus her thoughts did into queſtion call:</l>
                  <l>What means can be attempted or appli'd</l>
                  <l>To this my ſtrange calamity, beſide</l>
                  <l>What is already us'd? for though they wood,</l>
                  <l>The gods themſelves can render me no good:</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:44380:33"/>
                  <l>Why then should I proceed, and unawares</l>
                  <l>Tender my foot unto ſo many ſnares?</l>
                  <l>What darkneſs can protect me? what diſguiſe</l>
                  <l>Hide me from her inevitable eyes?</l>
                  <l>Some women from their crimes can courage gather,</l>
                  <l>Then why not I from miſery? and rather,</l>
                  <l>What I cannot defer, not long withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Yield up my ſelf a priſoner to her hand.</l>
                  <l>For timely modeſty may mitigate</l>
                  <l>That rage, which abſence does exaſperate.</l>
                  <l>And to confirm this, who knows whether he,</l>
                  <l>Whom my ſoul longs for, with his mother be?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> now ſick of earthly buſineſs,</l>
                  <l>Commands her Coach be put in readineſs:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſubtil ſtructure was all wrought upon</l>
                  <l>With gold, with purple, and vermillion.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vulcan</hi> compos'd the fabrick, 'twas the ſame</l>
                  <l>He gave his wife when he a wooing came.</l>
                  <l>Then of thoſe many hundred Doves that ſoar</l>
                  <l>About her palace, she ſelected four,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe checker'd necks to the ſmall traces ti'd,</l>
                  <l>With nimble gyres they up to heaven did glide:</l>
                  <l>A world of Sparrows did by <hi>Venus</hi> flie,</l>
                  <l>And Nightingales that ſung melodiouſly;</l>
                  <l>And other birds accompani'd her Coach,</l>
                  <l>With pleaſant noiſe proclaiming her approach:</l>
                  <l>For neither hardy Eagle, Hawk, nor Kite,</l>
                  <l>Durſt her ſweet ſounding family afright.</l>
                  <l>The clovvds gave vvay, and heaven vvas open made</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Venus Joves</hi> high turrets did invade.</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:44380:33"/>
                  <l>Then having ſilenc'd her obſterperous quire,</l>
                  <l>She boldly calls for <hi>Mercury</hi> the crier,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joves</hi> meſſenger, who but a while before</l>
                  <l>Return'd with a looſe arrant, which be bore</l>
                  <l>To a new Miſtreſs, and was now t' adviſe</l>
                  <l>Upon ſome trick, to hide from <hi>Juno</hi>'s eyes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joves</hi> baudery, for he ſuch fears can do,</l>
                  <l>Which are his vertues, and his office to.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> ſaw him, ſhe much joy did ſhow,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid, kind brother <hi>Mercury,</hi> you know,</l>
                  <l>How I eſteem your love, at no ſmall rate,</l>
                  <l>With whom my mind I ſtill communicate:</l>
                  <l>Without whoſe counſel I have nothing done,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill preferr'd your admonition.</l>
                  <l>And now you muſt aſſiſt me; there's a maid</l>
                  <l>Lies hid, whom I have long time ſought, and laid</l>
                  <l>Cloſe wait to apprehend, but cannot take;</l>
                  <l>Therefore I'de have you proclamation make,</l>
                  <l>With a reward propounded, to requite,</l>
                  <l>Who e're ſhall bring, and ſet her in my fight.</l>
                  <l>Make known her marks, and age, leſt any chance,</l>
                  <l>Or after dare to protend ignorance.</l>
                  <l>Thus having ſaid, ſhe gave to him a note,</l>
                  <l>And libell, wherein <hi>Pſiche</hi>'s name was wrote.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hermes</hi> the powerful, and al-charming <hi>god</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Taking in hand his ſoul conſtraining rod,</l>
                  <l>With which he carries, and brings back from hell,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Venus</hi> went, for he lov'd <hi>Venus</hi> well;</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe he in former time her love had won,</l>
                  <l>And in his dalliance, had of her ſon</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:44380:34"/>
                  <l>Begot, call'd the <hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi> which is</l>
                  <l>The Boy, that was belov'd by <hi>Salmacis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus both from heaven deſcended, open cry,</l>
                  <l>In expreſs words, was made by <hi>Mercury.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O yes, if any can true tidings bring</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Venus</hi> hand-maid, daughter to a King,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pſiche</hi> the fugitive, of ſtature tall,</l>
                     <l>Of tender age, and form celeſtial:</l>
                     <l>To whom, for dowry, Art and Nature gave</l>
                     <l>All grace, and all the comlineſs they have.</l>
                     <l>This I was bid to ſay, and be it ſpoken</l>
                     <l>Without all envy, each ſmile is a token</l>
                     <l>Sufficient to betray her. In her gate</l>
                     <l>She <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſiſter does moſt imitate.</l>
                     <l>Nor does her voice ſound mortal, if you ſpy</l>
                     <l>Her face, you may diſcern her by the eye,</l>
                     <l>That like a ſtar, dazels the Optick ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> has oft his Torch brought lighted thence.</l>
                     <l>If any find her out, let him repair</l>
                     <l>Straight ways to <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the news declare;</l>
                     <l>And for his recompence, he ſhall have leave,</l>
                     <l>Even from <hi>Venus</hi> own lips, to receive</l>
                     <l>Seven fragrant kiſſes, and the reſt among,</l>
                     <l>One honey-kiſſe, and one touch from her tongue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which being publiſhed, the great deſire</l>
                  <l>Of this reward, ſet all mens hearts on fire.</l>
                  <l>So that poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> durſt no more forbear</l>
                  <l>To offer up her ſelf: then drawing near</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:44380:34"/>
                  <l>To <hi>Venus</hi> houſe, a Maid of hers, by name.</l>
                  <l>Call'd <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> when ſhe ſaw her, did exclaime,</l>
                  <l>O Madam <hi>Pſiche, Jove</hi> your honour ſave:</l>
                  <l>What do you feel now, you a Miſtreſs have?</l>
                  <l>Or does your raſhneſs, or your ignorant worth</l>
                  <l>Not know the pains we took to find you forth?</l>
                  <l>Sweet, you ſhall for your ſtubborneſs be taught:</l>
                  <l>With that rude hold upon her locks ſhe caught,</l>
                  <l>And drag'd her in, and before <hi>Venus</hi> brought.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>The ſecond Section.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO ſoon as <hi>Venus</hi> ſaw her, ſhe, like one</l>
                  <l>That looks 'twixt ſcorn and indignation,</l>
                  <l>Rais'd a loud laughter, ſuch as does proceed</l>
                  <l>From one, that is vex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> furiouſly indeed.</l>
                  <l>Then shaking of her head, biting her thumb,</l>
                  <l>She ſaid, what my good daughter, are you come</l>
                  <l>Your Mother to ſalute? But I believe,</l>
                  <l>You would your husband viſit, who does grieve</l>
                  <l>For the late burn, with which you did inure</l>
                  <l>His tender shoulder. But yet reſt ſecure;</l>
                  <l>I shall provide for you, nor will I ſwerve</l>
                  <l>From any needful office you deſerve.</l>
                  <l>Thus winking <hi>Venus</hi> did on <hi>Pſiche</hi> leer,</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch cruel kindneſs did her jeer.</l>
                  <l>Then for her entertainment, crys, where are</l>
                  <l>My two rough hand-maids, <hi>Solitude,</hi> and <hi>Care?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They enter'd; she commands her hands to tye,</l>
                  <l>And take the poor Maid to their cuſtody.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:44380:35"/>
                  <l>Which done accordingly, with whips they beat,</l>
                  <l>And her with torments miſerably intreat.</l>
                  <l>Thus us'd, and in this ſhameful manner dight,</l>
                  <l>They her, with ſcorn, reduce to <hi>Venus</hi> ſight:</l>
                  <l>Who ſmiling ſaid, 'tis more than time, that I</l>
                  <l>Should ſet my Nymphs all to work ſempſtery,</l>
                  <l>And make your Baby-clouts: why this is brave,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall <hi>Juno</hi> for your Mid-wife have.</l>
                  <l>Where will you lie in? how far are you gone?</l>
                  <l>That's a great motive to compaſſion.</l>
                  <l>And I my ſtile muſt rather boaſt, than ſmother,</l>
                  <l>That in my youth ſhall be call'd Grandmother.</l>
                  <l>But by your leave, I doubt theſe Marriages,</l>
                  <l>That are ſolemniz'd without witneſſes:</l>
                  <l>Without conſent of friends, the parties ſtate</l>
                  <l>Unequal to, are ſcarce legitimate,</l>
                  <l>And ſo this child, they ſhall a baſtard call:</l>
                  <l>If yet thou bringſt forth any child at all.</l>
                  <l>Then to begin with ſome revenge, ſhe roſe;</l>
                  <l>And all her ornaments did diſcompoſe,</l>
                  <l>And her diſcolour'd Gown in pieces pull,</l>
                  <l>And whatſoever made her beautifull.</l>
                  <l>But leaſt her ſufferings ſhould all paſſive be,</l>
                  <l>She turns her puniſhment to induſtry,</l>
                  <l>And takes of ſeveral Seeds, a certain meaſure;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wheat, Barley, Oates,</hi> and a confuſed treaſure</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Peaſe,</hi> and <hi>Lentiles,</hi> then all mixt, did pour</l>
                  <l>Into one heap; with a prefixed hour,</l>
                  <l>That ere her ſelf ſhould on our Hemiſphear,</l>
                  <l>That might as the bright evening Star appear.</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:44380:35"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſiche</hi> each Grain ſhould rightly ſegregate,</l>
                  <l>A taſque for twenty to elaborate.</l>
                  <l>This work aſſign'd, <hi>Venus</hi> from thence did paſs,</l>
                  <l>To a Marriage Feaſt, where ſhe invited was.</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> all alone amaz'd did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Nor to this labour would once ſet her hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n her own thoughts judging her ſelf unable,</l>
                  <l>To vanpuiſh that, was ſo inextricable;</l>
                  <l>VVhen lo, a numerous multitude of <hi>Ants,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her neighbours, the next fields inhabitants,</l>
                  <l>Came thronging in, ſent thither by ſome power,</l>
                  <l>That pity took on <hi>Cupid</hi>'s <hi>Paramour.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor would that wrong ſhould be without defence,</l>
                  <l>And hated <hi>Venus</hi> for her inſolence.</l>
                  <l>All theſe by an inſtinct together met,</l>
                  <l>Themſelves in a tumultuous method ſet</l>
                  <l>On work, and each grain <hi>Arithmetically</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Subſtract, Divide, and after Multiply.</l>
                  <l>And when that this was done, away they fled:</l>
                  <l>Each grain by its kind diſtinguiſhed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> now from the Nuptial feaſt was come,</l>
                  <l>Her breath perfum'd with wine, and <hi>Balſamum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her body was with twines of <hi>Mirtles</hi> bound,</l>
                  <l>Her head with Garlands of ſweet <hi>Roſes</hi> crown'd.</l>
                  <l>And ſeeing this accompliſht task, ſhe ſaid</l>
                  <l>Huſwife, 'twas not your handy work convay'd</l>
                  <l>Theſe Seeds in order thus, but his, that ſtill</l>
                  <l>Perſiſts in love, to thine, and his own ill.</l>
                  <l>Then on the ground ſhe threw a cruſt of bread,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pſiche</hi>'s ſupper, and ſo went to bed.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:44380:36"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> the while, in a back room was put</l>
                  <l>Under the ſame roof, and in priſon shut:</l>
                  <l>A punishment for his old luxury,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt he with <hi>Pſiche</hi> should accompany:</l>
                  <l>And ſo by too much ſtraining of his ſide,</l>
                  <l>Might hurt his wound, before 'twas ſcarrifi'd:</l>
                  <l>But when the Roſie morning drew away,</l>
                  <l>The ſable curtain, which let in the day,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> to <hi>Pſiche</hi> calls, and bids awake,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtanding up, she shews to her a Lake,</l>
                  <l>Environ'd with a rock, beyond whoſe ſteep</l>
                  <l>And craggy bottome, graz'd a flock of sheep:</l>
                  <l>They had no shepheard, them to feed or fold,</l>
                  <l>And yet their well-groan fleeces were of gold.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallas</hi> ſometimes, the precious locks would cull,</l>
                  <l>To make great <hi>Juno</hi> veſtures of the wooll:</l>
                  <l>Fetch me, ſays <hi>Venus,</hi> ſome of that rich hair,</l>
                  <l>But how you'l do it, I nor know, nor care.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> obeys, not out of hope to win,</l>
                  <l>So great a prize, but meaning to leap in,</l>
                  <l>That in the marish she might end her life,</l>
                  <l>And ſo be free'd from <hi>Venus,</hi> and her ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>When drawing near, the wind inſpired reed,</l>
                  <l>Spake with a tuneful voice, <hi>Pſiche</hi> take heed,</l>
                  <l>Let not deſpair thee of thy ſoul beguile,</l>
                  <l>Nor theſe my waters with thy death defile:</l>
                  <l>But reſt thee here, under this Willow-tree,</l>
                  <l>That growing drinks of the ſame ſtream with me;</l>
                  <l>Keep from thoſe sheep, that heated with the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Rage like the <hi>Lion,</hi> or the <hi>Scorpion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:44380:36"/>
                  <l>None can their ſtony brows, nor horns abide,</l>
                  <l>Till the days fire be ſomewhat qualifi'd.</l>
                  <l>But when the vapour, and their thirſt is quencht,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> horſes in the Ocean drencht,</l>
                  <l>Then you may fetch, what <hi>Venus</hi> does deſire,</l>
                  <l>And find their fleecy gold on every bryer:</l>
                  <l>Th' oraculous Reed full of humanity,</l>
                  <l>Thus from her hollow wombe did Propheſie:</l>
                  <l>And ſhe obſerving ſtrictly what was taught,</l>
                  <l>Her apron full of the ſoft mettle brought,</l>
                  <l>And gave to <hi>Venus;</hi> yet her gift and labour</l>
                  <l>Gain'd no acceptance, nor found any favour.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> know the author of this fact, ſays ſhe,</l>
                  <l>How 'twas the price of his adultery.</l>
                  <l>But now I will a ſerious trial make,</l>
                  <l>Whether you do theſe dangers undertake</l>
                  <l>With courage, and that wiſdome you pretend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or ſee that lofty Mountain, whence deſcend</l>
                  <l>Black-colour'd waters, from earth horrid dens,</l>
                  <l>And with their boilings waſh the <hi>Stygian</hi> fens.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom thence augment <hi>Cocytus</hi> foaming rage,</l>
                  <l>And ſwell his channel with their ſurpluſſage.</l>
                  <l>Go now, and ſome of that dead liquor skim,</l>
                  <l>And fill this chriſtal Pitcher to the brim:</l>
                  <l>Bring it me ſtraight, and ſo her brows did knit,</l>
                  <l>Threatning great matters if ſhe fail'd of it.</l>
                  <l>With this injunction <hi>Pſiche</hi> went her ways,</l>
                  <l>Hoping even there to end her wretched days.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut coming near to the prefixed place,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe height did court the clouds, and loweſt baſe,</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:44380:37"/>
                  <l>Gave thoſe black ſtreams their firſt original,</l>
                  <l>That wearing the hard rocks, did headlong fall</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Stygian</hi> vallies, underneath</l>
                  <l>She ſaw a fatal thing, and full of death.</l>
                  <l>Two watchful Dragons the ſtraight paſſage kept,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes were never ſeal'd, nor ever ſlept.</l>
                  <l>The waters too ſaid ſomething, <hi>Pſiche,</hi> flye;</l>
                  <l>What do you here? depart or you ſhall dye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> with terrour of the voice dejected,</l>
                  <l>And thought of that might never be effected,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Niobe,</hi> was chang'd into a ſtone,</l>
                  <l>In body preſent, but her mind was gone.</l>
                  <l>And in the midſt of her great grief, and fears,</l>
                  <l>Could not enjoy the comfort of her tears.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Jove,</hi> whoſe ſtill protecting providence</l>
                  <l>Is ever ready to help innocence:</l>
                  <l>Sent the <hi>Saturnian</hi> Eagle, who once led</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Love</hi>'s impulſion, ſnatcht up <hi>Ganimed</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be <hi>Jove</hi>'s Cup-bearer, from <hi>Ida</hi> hill,</l>
                  <l>And ever ſince bore <hi>Cupid</hi> a good will:</l>
                  <l>And what he could not to his perſon ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd upon his Miſtreſs to beſtow.</l>
                  <l>Then with Angelick ſpeed, when he had left</l>
                  <l>Aires high tracts, and the three Regions cleft,</l>
                  <l>Before her face he on the meadow ſate,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid, alaſs, thou inconſiderate,</l>
                  <l>And fooliſh Maid, return back, go not nigh</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſacred ſtreams, ſo full of majeſty.</l>
                  <l>What hope haſt thou thoſe waters to procure,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf does tremble to abjure?</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:44380:37"/>
                  <l>No mortal hand may be allow'd to touch,</l>
                  <l>Much leſs to ſteal a drop, their power is ſuch.</l>
                  <l>Give me the Pitcher, ſhe it gave; he went</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Stix,</hi> and fain'd that <hi>Venus</hi> had him ſent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> the Urne did to his tallons tye,</l>
                  <l>Then with his plumed oats poiz'd equally,</l>
                  <l>He lets it ſink betwixt the very jaws</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe fierce Dragons, and then up it draws,</l>
                  <l>And gives it <hi>Pſiche;</hi> ſhe the ſame convay'd</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Venus,</hi> yet her pains were ill apaid;</l>
                  <l>Nothing her rage might expiate, but ſtill</l>
                  <l>The end of one begins another ill.</l>
                  <l>For ought, ſays <hi>Venus,</hi> that I gather can,</l>
                  <l>You are a Witch, or ſome Magitian.</l>
                  <l>What elſe can be concluded out of theſe</l>
                  <l>Experienc'd impoſſibilities?</l>
                  <l>If your commerce be ſuch then, you may venter</l>
                  <l>Boldly to Hell, and when you there ſhall enter,</l>
                  <l>Me to my couſen <hi>Proſerpine</hi> commend,</l>
                  <l>And in my name intreat her ſhe would ſend</l>
                  <l>Some of her Box of beauty to me; ſay,</l>
                  <l>So much as may ſuffice me for a day:</l>
                  <l>Excuſe me to her, that my own is ſpent,</l>
                  <l>I know not how, by an ill accident,</l>
                  <l>I am aſham'd to ſpeak it, but 'tis gone,</l>
                  <l>And waſted all in curing of my Son.</l>
                  <l>But be not ſlack in your return; for I</l>
                  <l>Muſt with the <hi>gods</hi> feaſt of neceſſity.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I thither go, without diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Till I have us'd ſome art unto my face.</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:44380:38"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> conceiv'd now, that her life, and fate,</l>
                  <l>And fortunes all were at their utmoſt date,</l>
                  <l>Being by <hi>Venus</hi> cruelty thruſt on,</l>
                  <l>Towards a manifeſt deſtruction:</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe collects by argument, that thus</l>
                  <l>With her own feet, muſt march to <hi>Taenarus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this deluſive agony ſhe roſe,</l>
                  <l>And by degrees, up to a Turret goes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe top ore-look't the hills, it was ſo high,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd to tumble headlong from the sky:</l>
                  <l>Conceiting as her fancy did her feed,</l>
                  <l>That was the way to go to Hell indeed.</l>
                  <l>But then a ſuddain voice to her did call,</l>
                  <l>Which brake out of the cavernes of the wall,</l>
                  <l>That ſaid, ah coward wretch, why doſt thou yeild</l>
                  <l>To this laſt labour, and forſake the field?</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Victory</hi> her Banner does diſplay,</l>
                  <l>And with a profer'd Crown, tempts thee to ſtay.</l>
                  <l>The way to Hell is eaſie, and the gate</l>
                  <l>Stands ope; but if the ſoul be ſeparate</l>
                  <l>Once from the body, true, ſhe goes to Hell:</l>
                  <l>Not to return, but there for ever dwell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vertue</hi> knows no ſuch ſtop, nor they, whom <hi>Jove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Either begot, or equally does love.</l>
                  <l>Now lift to me; there is a fatal ground</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Greece,</hi> beyond <hi>Achaja</hi>'s fartheſt bound,</l>
                  <l>Near <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> famous for the rape</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> on <hi>Hellen</hi> made, and their eſcape.</l>
                  <l>'Tis quickly found; for with its ſteemy breath</l>
                  <l>It blaſts the fields, and is the port of death.</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:44380:38"/>
                  <l>The path, like <hi>Ariadnes</hi> clue does guide</l>
                  <l>To the dark Court, where <hi>Pluto</hi> does abide:</l>
                  <l>And if you muſt thoſe diſmall regions ſee,</l>
                  <l>Then carry in your hand a double fee.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Charon</hi> will do nothing without money;</l>
                  <l>And you muſt have ſops made of meal and honey.</l>
                  <l>It is a doubtful paſſage, for there are</l>
                  <l>Many Degrees, and Laws peculiar</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſtrictly be obſerv'd; and if once broke,</l>
                  <l>No ranſome, nor entreaty can revoke.</l>
                  <l>Nor is there proſecution of more ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>But all are penal Statutes on your life.</l>
                  <l>The firſt as you ſhall meet with, as you paſſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s an old man come driving of an Aſſe,</l>
                  <l>Decrepid as himſelf, they both ſhall ſweat</l>
                  <l>With their hard labour, and he ſhall intreat,</l>
                  <l>That you would help his burthen to unty;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut give no ear, nor ſtay when you go by.</l>
                  <l>And next you ſhall arrive without delay</l>
                  <l>To ſlow <hi>Avernu</hi>'s Lake, where you muſt pay</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>haron</hi> his waftage, as before I ſaid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or avarice does live among the dead:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd a poor man, though tyde ſerve, and the wind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he no ſtipend bring, muſt ſtay behind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere as you ſail along, you ſhall ſee one</l>
                  <l>Of ſqualid hue, they call <hi>Oblivion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eave up his hands, and on the waters float,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raying, you would receive him in your Boat:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut know, all thoſe that will in ſafety be,</l>
                  <l>Muſt learn to diſaffect ſuch piety.</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:44380:39"/>
                  <l>When you are landed, and a little paſt</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Stygian</hi> Ferry, you your eyes shall caſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſpy ſome buſie at their wheel, and theſe</l>
                  <l>Are three old women, call'd the Deſtinies;</l>
                  <l>They will deſire you to ſit down, and ſpin,</l>
                  <l>And shew your own lifes thread upon the pin.</l>
                  <l>Yet are they all but ſnares, and do proceed</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> malice, to corrupt your creed.</l>
                  <l>For should you lend your help to ſpin, or card,</l>
                  <l>Or meddle with their diſtaff, your reward</l>
                  <l>Might perhaps ſlip out of your hand, and then</l>
                  <l>You muſt hope never to come back again.</l>
                  <l>Next, a huge Maſtiff shall you ſee before</l>
                  <l>The Palace-gare, and <hi>Adamantine</hi> door,</l>
                  <l>That leads to <hi>Dis,</hi> who when he opens wide</l>
                  <l>His treple throat, the ghoſts are terrifi'd</l>
                  <l>With his loud barkins, which ſo far rebound,</l>
                  <l>They make all Hell to Eccho with their ſound:</l>
                  <l>Him with a morſel you muſt firſt aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>And then deliver <hi>Venus</hi> Embaſſage.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Proſerpine</hi> shall kindly you intreat,</l>
                  <l>And will provide a banquet, and a ſeat.</l>
                  <l>But if you ſit, ſit on the ground, and taſte</l>
                  <l>None of her dainties, but declare in haſte</l>
                  <l>VVhat you deſire, which she will ſtraight deliver:</l>
                  <l>Then with thoſe former rules, paſs back the river.</l>
                  <l>Give the three-headed dog his other share,</l>
                  <l>And to the greedy Marriner his fare.</l>
                  <l>Keep faſt theſe precepts whatſoever they be,</l>
                  <l>And think on <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Euridice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:44380:39"/>
                  <l>But above all things, this obſerve to do,</l>
                  <l>Take heed, you open not, nor pry into</l>
                  <l>The beauties Box, elſe shall you there remain,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſee this Heaven, nor theſe Stars again.</l>
                  <l>The ſtone incloſed voice, did friendly thus</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> forewarn, with ſigns propitious.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The laſt Section.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO ſoon as <hi>Pſiche</hi> got all things together,</l>
                  <l>That might be uſeful for her going thither,</l>
                  <l>And her return, to <hi>Taenarus</hi> she went,</l>
                  <l>And the Infernal paſſage did attempt:</l>
                  <l>VVhere all thoſe ſtrange, and fatal propheſies</l>
                  <l>Accomplisht were in their occurrences.</l>
                  <l>For firſt she paſſes by with careleſs ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>The old man, and his Aſſe, and gave no heed</l>
                  <l>Either unto his perſon, or deſire.</l>
                  <l>And next she pays the Ferry-man his hire;</l>
                  <l>And though oblivion and the Fates did wo her,</l>
                  <l>VVith many ſtrong temptations to undo her,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liſſes</hi> like, she did their prayers decline,</l>
                  <l>And came now to the houſe of <hi>Proſerpine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before the Palace was a ſtately Court,</l>
                  <l>Where forty Marble-pillars did ſupport</l>
                  <l>The roof and frontiſ-piece, that bore on high</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pluto</hi>'s own ſtatue, grav'd in Ebony.</l>
                  <l>His face, though full of majeſty, was dim'd</l>
                  <l>VVith a ſad cloud, and his rude throne un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rim'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>His golden Scepter was eat in with ruſt,</l>
                  <l>And that again quite overlaid with duſt.</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:44380:40"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceres</hi> was wrought him by, with weeping eyne,</l>
                  <l>Lamenting for the loſs of <hi>Proſerpine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her daughters rape was there ſet down at full,</l>
                  <l>Who while that ſhe too ſtudiouſly did pull</l>
                  <l>The purple Violet, and ſanguine Roſe,</l>
                  <l>Lillies, and low grown Panſies; to compoſe</l>
                  <l>VVreaths for the Nymphs, regardles of her health</l>
                  <l>'Twas ſoon ſurpriz'd, and ſnatcht away by ſtealth.</l>
                  <l>Forc'd by the King of the infernal powers,</l>
                  <l>And ſeem'd to cry, and look after her flowers.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enceladus</hi> was ſtrecht upon his back,</l>
                  <l>VVhile <hi>Plutoes</hi> Horſe-hoofs, and Coach did wrack</l>
                  <l>His bruiſed body. <hi>Pallas</hi> did extend</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Gorgons</hi> head. <hi>Delia</hi> her bow did bend;</l>
                  <l>And Virgins both, their Uncle did defy</l>
                  <l>Like Champions, to defend virginity.</l>
                  <l>The Sun, and Stars were wrapt in ſable weeds.</l>
                  <l>Dampt with the breath of his <hi>Tanarian</hi> Steeds.</l>
                  <l>All theſe, and more were portray'd round about,</l>
                  <l>VVhich filth defac'd, or time had eaten out.</l>
                  <l>Three headed <hi>Cerberus</hi> the gate did keep,</l>
                  <l>VVhom <hi>Pſiche</hi> with a ſop firſt laid to ſleep;</l>
                  <l>And then went ſafely by, where firſt ſhe ſaw</l>
                  <l>Hells Judges ſit, and urging of the law:</l>
                  <l>The place was parted in two ſeveral ways,</l>
                  <l>The right hand to <hi>Elyſium</hi> convays;</l>
                  <l>But on the left, were malefactors ſent,</l>
                  <l>The ſeat of tortures, and ſtrange puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Tantalus</hi> ſtands thirſty to the chin,</l>
                  <l>In water, but can take no l'quor in.</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44380:40"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ixion</hi> too, and <hi>Siſiphus;</hi> the one</l>
                  <l>A wheel, the other turns a reſtleſs ſtone.</l>
                  <l>A Vulture there on <hi>Titius</hi> does wreak</l>
                  <l>The God's juſt wrath, and pounding with his beak,</l>
                  <l>On his immortal liver ſtill does feed,</l>
                  <l>For what the day does waſt, the night does breed:</l>
                  <l>And other ſouls are forced to reveal,</l>
                  <l>VVhat unjuſt pleaſures they on Earth did ſteal;</l>
                  <l>VVhom fiery <hi>Phlegeton</hi> does round incloſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Stix</hi> his waves does nine times interpoſe.</l>
                  <l>The noiſe of whips, and Furies, did ſo fright</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Pſiche</hi> ears, ſhe haſted to the right.</l>
                  <l>That path way ſtraight, for on each ſide there grew</l>
                  <l>A Grove of mournful <hi>Cypreſs</hi> and of <hi>Yew:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is the place of ſuch as happy dy.</l>
                  <l>There, as ſhe walked on, did Infants cry,</l>
                  <l>VVhom cruel death ſnacht from their teats away,</l>
                  <l>And rob'd of ſweet life, in an evil day,</l>
                  <l>There Lovers live, who living here, were wiſe;</l>
                  <l>And had their Ladies, to cloſe up their eyes.</l>
                  <l>There Mighty <hi>Heroes</hi> walk, that ſpent their blood,</l>
                  <l>In a juſt cauſe, and for their Countries good.</l>
                  <l>All theſe beholding through the glimering air,</l>
                  <l>A moral; and ſo exquiſitely fair,</l>
                  <l>Thick as the motes, in the Sun beams came running</l>
                  <l>To gaze, and know the cauſe too of her coming;</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe diſſembled, only askt to know,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Plato</hi> dwelt, for thither ſhe muſt go:</l>
                  <l>A guide was ſtraight aſſign'd, who did attend,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Pſiche</hi> brought ſafe to her journies end,</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:44380:41"/>
                  <l>Who being entred, proſtrate on her knee,</l>
                  <l>She humbly tenders <hi>Venus</hi> Embaſly.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Plutoes</hi> Queen preſented to her gueſt,</l>
                  <l>A Princely <hi>Throne</hi> to ſit on, and a feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing her taſte, and her tyr'd limbs refreſh,</l>
                  <l>After her journey, and her wearineſs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> excus'd it, that ſhe could no ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And if ſhe had her errand would away.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Proſerpine</hi> reply'd, you do not know</l>
                  <l>Fair Maid, the joys and pleaſures are below,</l>
                  <l>Stay and poſſeſs whatever I call mine,</l>
                  <l>For other Lights, and other Stars do ſhine</l>
                  <l>Within our territories, the day's not loſt,</l>
                  <l>As you imagine, in the <hi>Elyſian</hi> coaſt.</l>
                  <l>The Golden <hi>Age,</hi> and Progeny is here,</l>
                  <l>And that Fam'd <hi>Tree,</hi> that does in <hi>Autumn</hi> bear</l>
                  <l>Cluſters of Gold, whoſe <hi>Apples</hi> thou ſhalt hoard,</l>
                  <l>Or each meal, if thou pleaſe, ſet on the board.</l>
                  <l>The Matrons of <hi>Elyſium</hi> at thy beck,</l>
                  <l>Shall come and go; and buried Queens ſhall deck</l>
                  <l>Thy body, in more ſtately ornaments,</l>
                  <l>Then all Earths feigned Majeſty preſents:</l>
                  <l>The pale and ſqualid region ſhall rejoyce,</l>
                  <l>Silence ſhall break forth a pleaſant voice:</l>
                  <l>Stern <hi>Pluto</hi> ſhall himſelf to mirth betake,</l>
                  <l>And crowned Gheſts ſhall banquet for thy ſake;</l>
                  <l>New Lamps ſhall burn, if thou wilt here abide,</l>
                  <l>And nights thick darkneſs ſhall be rarifi'd,</l>
                  <l>What ere the winds upon the earth do ſweep</l>
                  <l>Rivers, or Fens embrace, or the vaſt deep,</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:44380:41"/>
                  <l>Shall be thy tribute, and I will deliver</l>
                  <l>Up for thy ſervant the <hi>Lethean</hi> River:</l>
                  <l>Beſides the <hi>Parcae</hi> ſhall thy hand-maids be,</l>
                  <l>And what thou ſpeak'ſt ſtand for a deſtiny.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pſiche</hi> gave thanks, but did her plainly tell,</l>
                  <l>She would not be a Courtier unto hell:</l>
                  <l>When wondring that ſuch honours did not pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>She offer'd gifts far richer then all theſe.</l>
                  <l>For as a Dowry at her feet ſhe laid</l>
                  <l>The mighty engines which the world upweigh'd,</l>
                  <l>And vow'd to give her immortality,</l>
                  <l>And all the pleaſures and the royalty</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields; which wiſely ſhe</l>
                  <l>Reſus'd, for hell, with all their power and skill,</l>
                  <l>Though they allure, they cannot force the will.</l>
                  <l>This vex'd fair <hi>Proſerpine</hi> any ſhould know</l>
                  <l>Their horrid ſecrets, and have power to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Unto the upper world what she had ſeen</l>
                  <l>Of hell and <hi>Styx,</hi> of <hi>Pluto</hi> and his Queen:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſince she might not her own Laws withſtand,</l>
                  <l>She gave the box of beauty in her hand.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Pſiche</hi> with thoſe precepts us'd before,</l>
                  <l>The Sun's bright beams did once again adore.</l>
                  <l>Then, as ſhe thought, being out of all controul,</l>
                  <l>A curious raſhneſs did poſſeſs her ſoul,</l>
                  <l>That ſlighting of her charge and promis'd duty,</l>
                  <l>She greatly itch'd to adde to her own beauty;</l>
                  <l>Saying, Ah fool, to bear ſo rich a prize,</l>
                  <l>And yet through fear doſt envy thine own eyes</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:44380:42"/>
                  <l>The happy object, whoſe reflexion might</l>
                  <l>Gain thee ſome favour in young <hi>Cupid</hi>'s ſight:</l>
                  <l>The voice forbad me, but I now am free</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> viſion and Hell's cuſtody.</l>
                  <l>And ſo without all ſcruple she unlocks,</l>
                  <l>And lets forth the whole treaſure of the box,</l>
                  <l>Which was not any thing to make one fair,</l>
                  <l>But a meer <hi>Stygian</hi> and infernal air;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſubtle breathings through her pores did creep,</l>
                  <l>And ſtuft her body with a cloud of ſleep.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Cupid,</hi> now not able to endure</l>
                  <l>Her longer abſence, having gain'd his cure,</l>
                  <l>And prun'd his rufled wings, flew through the gare</l>
                  <l>Of his cloſe priſon, to ſeek out his Mate:</l>
                  <l>Where finding her in this dull Lethargy,</l>
                  <l>He drew the foggy vapour from her eye,</l>
                  <l>And that her ſtupid ſpirits might awake,</l>
                  <l>Did all the drouſie exhalation ſhake</l>
                  <l>From off her ſenſe; ſhe ſhut it up, and ſeal'd</l>
                  <l>The Box ſo faſt, it ne'r might be reveal'd.</l>
                  <l>Next with his harmleſs Dirt, ſmall as a pin,</l>
                  <l>He prick'd the ſuperficies of her skin,</l>
                  <l>Saying, what wondrous frailty does poſſeſs</l>
                  <l>This female kind, or rather wilfulneſs?</l>
                  <l>For loe, thy fooliſh curioſity</l>
                  <l>Has tempted thee again to perjury.</l>
                  <l>What proud exploit was this? what horrid fact?</l>
                  <l>Beſure, my mother <hi>Venus</hi> will exact</l>
                  <l>A ſtrict account of all that has been done,</l>
                  <l>Both of thy ſelf and thy Commiſſion.</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:44380:42"/>
                  <l>But yet for all this treſpaſs, be of cheer,</l>
                  <l>And in a humble duty perſevere;</l>
                  <l>Detain from <hi>Venus</hi> nought that is her own,</l>
                  <l>And for what elſe remains let me alone.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Pſiche</hi> by her Lover being ſent,</l>
                  <l>And waxing ſtrong through his encouragement,</l>
                  <l>The Box of beauty unto <hi>Venus</hi> brings,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Cupid</hi> did betake him to his wings:</l>
                  <l>For when he ſaw his mother ſo auſteer,</l>
                  <l>Forc'd by the violence of love and fear,</l>
                  <l>He pierc'd the Marble concave of the sky,</l>
                  <l>To heaven appeal'd, and did for juſtice cry,</l>
                  <l>Pleading his cauſe, and in the ſacred preſence</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf did his Love-ſuit commence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove</hi> at his ſight threw by his rays, ſo pure,</l>
                  <l>That no eyes but his own might them endure:</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Cupid</hi> thus beſpake, Great <hi>Jove,</hi> if I</l>
                  <l>Am born your true and lawful progeny;</l>
                  <l>If I have plaid between your arms, and ſate</l>
                  <l>Next to your ſelf, but ſince grown to a ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of riper years, have been thought fit to bear</l>
                  <l>An equal ſway, and move in the ſame ſphere</l>
                  <l>Of honour with you, by whoſe means, both men</l>
                  <l>And gods have trembled at my bow, as when</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf have darted Thunder-bolts, and ſlain</l>
                  <l>The earth-bred Gyants in the <hi>Phlegrian</hi> plain.</l>
                  <l>And when in ſeveral ſcales my ſhafts were laid</l>
                  <l>VVith your own <hi>Trident,</hi> neither has out-weigh'd.</l>
                  <l>I come not now that you ſhould either give,</l>
                  <l>Confirm, or adde to my prerogative:</l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:44380:43"/>
                  <l>But ſetting all command and power aſide,</l>
                  <l>Deſire by Law and Juſtice to be tri'd.</l>
                  <l>For whither elſe should I appeal? or bring</l>
                  <l>My cauſe, but to your ſelf, that are a King,</l>
                  <l>And father to us all, and can diſpence</l>
                  <l>What right you pleaſe in Court and Conſcience?</l>
                  <l>I have been wrong'd, and muſt with grief indite</l>
                  <l>My mother of much cruelty and ſpight</l>
                  <l>To me and my poor <hi>Pſiche:</hi> there's but one</l>
                  <l>In the whole world, that my affection</l>
                  <l>And fancy likes, where others do enjoy</l>
                  <l>So many; the diverſity does cloy</l>
                  <l>Their very appetite: yet who but owes</l>
                  <l>All his delight to me? and <hi>Venus</hi> knows,</l>
                  <l>By her own thoughts, the uncontroled fire</l>
                  <l>That reigns in youth, when <hi>Love</hi> does him inſpire;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhe without all pity or remorſe,</l>
                  <l>Me and my Miſtreſs labours to divorce.</l>
                  <l>I covet no one's Spouſe, nor have I taken</l>
                  <l>Another's Love; there's not a man forſaken,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>god,</hi> for my ſake, that bewails his dear,</l>
                  <l>Or bathes his ſpoiled boſome with a tear.</l>
                  <l>Then why should any me and my Love ſever,</l>
                  <l>That joyn all other hearts and loves together?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove</hi> heard him out, and did applaud his ſpeech,</l>
                  <l>And both his hand and ſcepter to him reach.</l>
                  <l>Then calling <hi>Cupid,</hi> his ſmooth fingers laid</l>
                  <l>On his <hi>Ambroſiack</hi> cheek, and kiſſing, ſaid,</l>
                  <l>My little youngſter, and my ſon, 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>That I have never yet receiv'd from you</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:44380:43"/>
                  <l>Any due reverence or reſpective meed,</l>
                  <l>Which all the other <hi>gods</hi> to me decreed.</l>
                  <l>For this my heart, whoſe high preheminence</l>
                  <l>Gives Edicts to the Stars, and does diſpence</l>
                  <l>The like to nature, your fine hand the while</l>
                  <l>With earthly luſts ſtill labours to defile;</l>
                  <l>And contrary to publick diſcipline,</l>
                  <l>And 'gainſt all Laws both Moral and Divine,</l>
                  <l>Chiefly the <hi>Julian;</hi> thou doſt fill mine eyes</l>
                  <l>With many foul and cloſe adulteries.</l>
                  <l>For how oft-times have I, through van deſire,</l>
                  <l>Been chang'd to beaſts, birds, ſerpents, and to fire?</l>
                  <l>Which has procur'd ill cenſures, and much blame,</l>
                  <l>And hurt my eſtimation and my ſame:</l>
                  <l>Yet being pleas'd with this thy foolish ſport,</l>
                  <l>I'm loath to leave it, though I'm ſorry for't;</l>
                  <l>And on condition thou wilt uſe thy wit</l>
                  <l>In my behalf, and mind the benefit,</l>
                  <l>I will perform all thy demands: if when</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeft fair Damſels on the earth agen,</l>
                  <l>Remembring thou waſt brought up on my knee,</l>
                  <l>That every ſuch Maid thou wilt bring to me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> aſſents. Then <hi>Jove</hi> bid's <hi>Maya</hi>'s ſon</l>
                  <l>Publiſh a royal Proclamation</l>
                  <l>Through the precincts of Heaven, and call at once</l>
                  <l>A general Councel and a Seſſions,</l>
                  <l>That the whole bench and race of deities,</l>
                  <l>Should in their ſeveral ranks and pedigrees</l>
                  <l>Repair ſtraight to his Court, this to be done</l>
                  <l>In pain of <hi>Jove</hi>'s diſpleaſure, and a ſum</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:44380:44"/>
                  <l>Of mony to be laid upon his head,</l>
                  <l>And from his lands and goods be levied,</l>
                  <l>If any <hi>god</hi> ſhould dare himſelf abſent,</l>
                  <l>For any cauſe, from this great <hi>Parliament:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that whoever had his name I' th' book</l>
                  <l>His fine, but his excuſe ſhould not be took.</l>
                  <l>This being nois'd abroad, from every where</l>
                  <l>The leſſer <hi>gods</hi> came thronging out of fear,</l>
                  <l>And the celeſtial Theatre did thwack,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Atlas</hi> ſeem'd to groan under his pack.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Jove</hi> out of his Ivory Throne did riſe,</l>
                  <l>And thus beſpake them, Conſcript deities,</l>
                  <l>For ſo the <hi>Muſes,</hi> with their whiteſt ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Have writ your names and titles every one.</l>
                  <l>You know my Nephew <hi>Cupid,</hi> for the moſt</l>
                  <l>Of us, I'm ſure, have felt him to our coſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe youthful heat I have ſtill ſought in vain,</l>
                  <l>And his licentious riot to reſtrain.</l>
                  <l>But that his leud life be no farther ſpread,</l>
                  <l>His luſts nor his corruptions publiſhed:</l>
                  <l>I hold it ſit that we the cauſe remove,</l>
                  <l>And bind him in the fetters of chaſte love:</l>
                  <l>And ſince that he has made ſo good a choice</l>
                  <l>Of his own wife, let each <hi>god</hi> give his voice,</l>
                  <l>That he enjoy her, and for ever tie</l>
                  <l>Unto himſelf in bands of matrimony.</l>
                  <l>Then unto <hi>Venus</hi> turning his bright face,</l>
                  <l>Daughter, he ſays, conceive it no diſgrace</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pſiche</hi> marries with your ſon; for I,</l>
                  <l>That where I pleaſe give immortality,</l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:44380:44"/>
                  <l>VVill alter her condition and her ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And make all equal and legitimate.</l>
                  <l>With that command to <hi>Mercury</hi> was given,</l>
                  <l>That he should fetch fair <hi>Pſiche</hi> unto heaven:</l>
                  <l>And when that ſhe into their preſence came,</l>
                  <l>Her wondrous beauty did each <hi>god</hi> inflame.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Jove</hi> reach'd forth a cup with <hi>Nectar</hi> fraught,</l>
                  <l>And bad her be immortal with the draught:</l>
                  <l>So joyn'd them hand in hand, and vow'd beſide,</l>
                  <l>That she with her dear <hi>Cupid</hi> should abide,</l>
                  <l>Ne'r to be ſeparate; and more t'enlarge</l>
                  <l>His bounty, made a feaſt at his own charge,</l>
                  <l>VVhere he plac'd <hi>Cupid</hi> at the upper end,</l>
                  <l>And amorous <hi>Pſiche</hi> on his boſom Iean'd.</l>
                  <l>Next ſate himſelf and <hi>Juno,</hi> then each gueſt:</l>
                  <l>And this great dinner was by <hi>Vulcan</hi> dreſs'd.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Graces</hi> ſtrew'd the room, and made it ſmile</l>
                  <l>VVith blushing Roſes and ſweet flowers, the while</l>
                  <l>The Spheres danc'd harmony. <hi>Apolle</hi> ran</l>
                  <l>Diviſion on his Harp, <hi>Satyr</hi> and <hi>Pan</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Plaid on their Pipes: the Quite of Muſes ſang,</l>
                  <l>And the vaſt concave of <hi>Olimpus</hi> rang</l>
                  <l>VVich pious acclamations to the Bride,</l>
                  <l>And joy'd that <hi>Pſiche</hi> was thus deiſi'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hermes</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> mov'd their graceful feet,</l>
                  <l>And did in artificial meaſures meet;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Phrygian</hi> Boy fill'd wine at this great Feaſt</l>
                  <l>Onely to <hi>Jove,</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> to the reſt.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Cupid</hi> had his Love, and not long after</l>
                  <l>Her womb, by <hi>Juno</hi>'s help, brought forth a daughter</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:44380:45"/>
                  <l>A child by nature different from all,</l>
                  <l>That laught when ſhe was born, and men did call</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> one that does exhilerate</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>gods</hi> and men, and doth her ſelf dilate</l>
                  <l>Through all ſocieties, chiefly the beſt,</l>
                  <l>Where there is any triumph, or a feaſt.</l>
                  <l>She was the <hi>Author</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> did firſt invent</l>
                  <l>All kind of ſport, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eits and merriment:</l>
                  <l>And ſince to all men's humours does incline,</l>
                  <l>Whether that they be ſenſual or divine.</l>
                  <l>Is of a modeſt and a looſe behaviour,</l>
                  <l>And of a ſetled and a wanton favour;</l>
                  <l>Moſt dangerous when she appears moſt kind,</l>
                  <l>For then ſhe'l part and leave a ſting behind:</l>
                  <l>But happy they that can her ſtill detain,</l>
                  <l>For where she is moſt fix'd she is leaſt vain.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:44380:45"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
